<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Strength made perfect in weakness In four sermons preached by William Hickocks M.A.</title>
            <author>[Hickocks, William, fl. 1674]</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1918A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896416</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2404:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Strength made perfect in weakness In four sermons preached by William Hickocks M.A.</title>
                  <author>[Hickocks, William, fl. 1674]</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst at the Three Crowns and Bible, at the lower end of Cheap-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page is A2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>STRENGTH MADE PERFECT IN Weakneſs.</p>
            <p>In Four Sermons Preached By <hi>William Hickocks</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Quandoquidem nobis denegatur diu vivere relinquamus aliquid quo nos vixiſſe teſtemur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sen.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the Three Crowns and Bible, at the Lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE worthy Author of theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Mr. <hi>William Hickocks,</hi> was Educated in the Schools of the Prophets, and that in an happy time, when the envious man was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Nurſeries, and Vine-yards, to poyſon and ſpoyle them, with the Tares of unſound Doctrines, and evil Examples; and it pleaſed God to Sanctifie his Liberal and Pious Education, that he became not onely a good Chriſtian, but alſo an able Miniſter, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit. He made the work of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, the work not only of his Head, but
<pb facs="tcp:154197:3"/> Heart too; ſhineing with the ſplendor of Knowledge and Holineſs, and burning with very Holy, Well-grounded, Affectionate, Zeal; giving himſelf to ſpend, and be ſpent; ready to impart his very ſoul and all, in Delivering and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rging his great Maſter's Errand. Obſerving his Spirit, (as I had frequent opportunity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with him) I often thought he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured too much of the other World, to be far from it; and ſo it was indeed. His Light was too bright and hot to last, his Race too ſwift and eager to hold; he threw himſelf with ſtrong girds before his feet, and ſoon apprehending the prize, left his Body behind. Great Labours, and Publick, as well as Perſonal deep Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments, exhauſted his Spirits, and quickly reduced his Body to the dregs of Melancholy, ſo that he was often (as <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> once) ſick even to death for the work of the Miniſtry. God alſo early called him forth (as <hi>David</hi> when but a ſtripling) to grapple with <hi>Goliah</hi>-like Temptations, wherein indeed he was Conqueror; but yet (as Christ) with great faintneſs of Spirit: the Lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:154197:3"/> ſeeing him weary, took him up in his arms and carried him home, excuſing him his otherwiſe-remaining travel. Oh! how precious had his experiences been, had he had Life and Health to acquaint us with them? Oh! the depth of the Wiſdom and Counſel of God, and his ways past find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out! that ſo fruitful a Tree ſhould not be ſpared! that a Veſſel of Mercy, and Honor, ſo purged and fitted for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters uſe, ſhould be daſhed in pieces, even as ſoon almoſt, as it was ſeaſoned and broached! But yet, bleſſed be God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Earthen Veſſel be broken, we have not loſt all the Treaſure; the leſs it is, that is ſaved, the more we ſhould make of it; as we carry it towards the Parents of many Children, when they leave but one onely little one behind, we account it very dear; eſpecially if it be like the Parent: and truly ſo is this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Book in thy hand; it being a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the Conſiſtency of Faith and Doubting, Fear and Hope, Heavineſs and Gladneſs, in one and the ſame Godly Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; whereof the Author was a famous
<pb facs="tcp:154197:4"/> Inſtance, as if this had been his very Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Complexion. Behold then here one onely little Birth (<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons being Publiſhed as they were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand.</note> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hurt indeed in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, for want of better Midwifry, but yet) of many, reſembling the Parent, and coſting him his very Life. Behold, Reader, I preſent thee with a taſte of the Fruit, under the waight whereof, the Tree did Bend, Break, and Fall; yet ſhall we anſwer at last, if we Refuſe, or Receive ſo coſtly Grace in vain. Oh! what a ſad account ſhall we have to make, if this man of God, and the many others which are lately taken from amongſt us, ſhould be gone to Heaven to complain of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankfulneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntractableneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfruitfulneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſteadfaſtneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby we have broken their Hearts. Good Reader, I warn in Paper and Inke, and would more gladly do it in Tears, if the Lord would pleaſe to hear Prayers, that we may be Reſtored to the free Publick Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Miniſtry, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154197:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>The ſecond Epiſtle of</hi> Paul <hi>to the</hi> Theſſalonians, <hi>the ſecond Chapter, the ſixteenth and ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Verſes.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father who hath loved us, and hath given us everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17.</hi> Comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is the duty of all, when they have the Truth made known to them, to receive it; ſo much more is it the duty of believers that have received the Truth, to hold it faſt: As we are to buy the Truth, ſo having once bought it, never to ſell it; as we are to lay hold on it, ſo never to let it go: as it is our duty to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Truth, ſo it ſhould be our care never to let it go, never to leave it.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having in this Chapter, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the Saints to ſteadfaſtneſs, to watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154197:5"/> and carefulneſs; he preſſeth his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, from variety of Motives, taken partly from the Apoſtaſie of thoſe that are ſeemingly friends to the Truth; partly from the miſery of the enemies of the Truth; and then again, in regard of the holyneſs they were adorned with, and the happineſs they ſhould ere long injoy; and therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats his exhortation to ſtedfaſtneſs, in the Verſe before the Text: [<hi>Therefore Brethren ſtand faſt, and hold the tradition (not of men but of God) which you have been taught,</hi> (that is thoſe Doctrines you have received) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from our mouths, or writings, that is from the Apoſtles, who were infallibly guided by the Holy Ghoſt: And to this Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he adds Supplication, in the words now read; wherein take notice of four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Perſons praying; <hi>Paul, Silva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> and <hi>Timotheus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Perſons prayed for; <hi>The Saints of the Church of the</hi> Theſſalonians.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Perſons prayed too; and they are two;
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, <hi>God the Son.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>God the Father.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle mentions the Son firſt, no<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he is ſo in order of Nature; but he <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not curious in placing his words, though <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154197:5"/> very well knew, that God the Father is the firſt Perſon in the Trinity; <hi>God even our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> where we have firſt, his Love aſſerted, <hi>[who hath loved us]</hi> Secondly, declared and illuſtrated; firſt, in the effects of it, <hi>[and hath given us everlaſting conſolation]</hi> and then in the cauſe of it, <hi>[and good hope through grace].</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The Petitions themſelves, or Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings prayed for; and they are two,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſolation,</hi> and <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſolation,</hi> comfort your Hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Confirmation,</hi> ſtabliſh you in every good Word and Work.</p>
            <p>My time is but ſhort, the Text is large, and therefore I muſt but only in many things para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe upon the Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt]</hi> Now or firſt, the Apoſtle here adds this Supplication to his former Exhortation; from whence I might note Firſt,</p>
            <p>Doct. I. <hi>That the Miniſters of the Goſpel are not only to Preach to, but to pray for the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As they are to ſpeak from God to them, ſo they are to ſpeak for them unto God: that great Prophet of the Church, our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154197:6"/> Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, did not only reveal his Fathers mind to his Diſciples, but often prayed and that earneſtly for them; as in that 17. <hi>Joh.</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> And if this be ſo, then by way of equity, People ought to pray for their Miniſter; but to paſs to the ſecond, after his exhorting them to ſtedfaſtneſs, he goes to Prayer; and it ſhews thus much, that <hi>Paul's</hi> exhortations to them, were not ſufficient of themſelves to ſtabliſh theſe Saints, without the grace of God; in as much as theſe things given in command to ſtedfaſtneſs, is backt by Prayer; it intimates how little theſe will prevail unleſs God touch the Heart: from whence we have this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</p>
            <p>Doct. II. <hi>That Miniſters Preaching, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s bleſſing, will do Peoples ſouls no good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The voice of Miniſters in Preaching is but an empty ſound, and though it come into our ears, will never reach the Heart, unleſs the doctrine have efficacy from the Spirit of Truth. Neither <hi>Paul</hi> or any of his fellow-labourers in the work of the Goſpel, will bring people into, or keep them in, the ways of the Lord, unleſs God bleſs their labours to that end: none of theſe bleſſed Apoſtles could by any of their own power, by the height or ſtrength of arguments, prevail with them, to obey the Goſpel; they could never convert to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154197:6"/> the Truth, or keep them in the Truth, unleſs God were pleaſed to turn their Hearts; this is clear by the Jews under the Old Teſtament, and the people under the New; the Word of God that came to the Jews, how often doth <hi>Iſaiah, Jeremiah, Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> and other Prophets, tell them of their ſins, but they would not hear; ſee how the Lord complains in the 17. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 25. <hi>Since the day that your Fathers came forth, out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>unto this day, I have ſent unto you, all my Servants the Prophets, daily, riſeing up early, and ſending them; yet they hearkned not unto me,</hi> &amp;c. for all they had ſo many meſſengers from God to them, and this too afterward repeated in ſeveral places, yet they did not hearken to God: neither when they were in their own Countrey, nor in a ſtrange Land: and ſo in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> here, <hi>That laboured more abundantly then they all;</hi> yet how inefficatious was it to many: when he Preached to the Jews, 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 45. <hi>ver. They were filled with envy, and spake againſt thoſe things, that were ſpoken by</hi> Paul, <hi>contradicting and blaspheming:</hi> And ſo among the Gentiles, inſtead of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with them to bring them to the Truth, he was perſecuted by them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Who is</hi> Paul, <hi>or who is</hi> Apollo; but Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by whom you believe: and though he did prevail with many, it was not of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but it was the Lord that gave the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154197:7"/> your believing, your getting grace, your growing and increaſing in holineſs, is only through the bleſſing of God: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of ſeveral places where he did good; he ſaith, when he came to ſuch or ſuch a place, there was a door opened to him; as a door of utterance to the Apoſtle, ſo a door of entrance to the People, that they received the Word of God: and though his commiſſion runs, <hi>That he might turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Sathan unto God,</hi> &amp;c. 26. <hi>Acts</hi> 18. yet he is only the inſtrumental cauſe, God is only the efficient cauſe; God alone commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs; he alone that is the heart ſearcher, is the heart changer; he opened <hi>Lydias</hi> heart: we need not go far to evidence this Truth, we need not go abroad, but ſtay at home, to ſee this ſad ſpectacle; how many faithful Preachers, hath God ſent to this Land of ours, for many ſcores of Years together, ſcarce any Nation under Heaven, hath had that plenty of Miniſters, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that <hi>England</hi> hath had, and that powerful Preaching, ſince the Apoſtles days, that we have had; and yet what little fruit to be ſeen: How many ſetled upon their Lees, and will not be brought off? he that was filthy is filthy ſtill: How great are the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, Lying, Swearing, Whoring, Drunkeneſs, &amp;c. How doth the love of many wax cold? How many back-ſliding from the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154197:7"/> Truth, and ways of God, what ever Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſay to the contrary? People, time after time have been call'd on to walk after the Spirit, and not after the Fleſh, yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to return: may not the Lord ſay to us, as to the Jews, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.4, 5, 6. <hi>verſes, What could have been done more to my Vine-yard, that I have not done in it? Wherefore when I looked that it ſhould bring forth Grapes, brought it forth Wild-grapes?</hi> I wiſh we have no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to take notice of the words following: <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>And now go to; I will tell you what I will do to my Vine-yard; I will take away the hedge thereof, and it ſhall be eaten up, and break down the wall of it, and it ſhall be troden down; verſ.</hi> 6, <hi>And I will lay it waſt, it ſhall not be pruned, nor digged, but there ſhall come up briers and thornes; I will alſo command the clouds that they rain no rain upon it;</hi> which judgment, God in his mercy prevent: it is true, Miniſters may do thus much; ſave their own ſouls, by taking heed to their Doctrine, and their lives, and by warning people of their ſins; and though Miniſters by Preaching, may leave people without excuſe, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay at the laſt day, Lord if we had known our duty we would have done it; Miniſters Preaching may add to Peoples ſufferings, they may increaſe their condemnation another day; but alas, it is not in the power of Miniſters, to affect Peoples hearts, or reform their lives; how earneſt then ſhould Miniſters and People
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154197:8"/> be, that when the Word of God is Preached, they ſhould pray that the power of God might accompany it; Peoples prayers ſhould be, that as God would ſend forth Labourers into his harveſt, ſo that God would make that food that's ſent them, to nouriſh their ſouls in ſpiritual life unto life eternal; <hi>for man lives not by bread only, but by the Word of God;</hi> as natural life is not preſerved through bread, without the concurance of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; ſo neither ſpiritual life, without the influence of his Spirit; the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is only able to ſtrike through our luſts, the weapons of our warfare, are only mighty through God. People had need pray, as for their Miniſters, that they may have a door of utterance; ſo for themſelves, that they may have a door of entrance; that with readineſs of mind, they may be brought to, and built up in their moſt holy Faith; that when the Goſpel comes by Preaching to them, it may come not only in word but in power of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whereas he prays not only to God the Father, but to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for theſe Saints comfort and eſtabliſhment: we have this Doctrine,</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That as God the Father, ſo the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is the author of the Saints graces and comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154197:8"/>
            <p>As the form of the Apoſtles ſalutations in moſt of his Epiſtles, is grace and peace from God our Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſo he concludes generally, the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Becauſe <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. <hi>It pleaſed the Father that in him ſhould all fullneſs dwell: Joh.</hi> 1.16. <hi>And of his fulneſs have all we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived grace for grace: Col.</hi> 2.9. <hi>For in him dwelleth all the fulneſs</hi> (not only the fulneſs of Divinity, but the fulneſs) <hi>of the Deity, of the Godhead bodily:</hi> that ſecond Perſon of the Trinity, who was true Man, was likewiſe true God, therefore he is the author of all good: from hence then (for it is very remarkeable his mentioning the Son) let us (I ſay) make this uſe of it; let us honour the Son, as we honour the Father; <hi>I and the Father are one</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.30. and the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7. ſaith of Chriſt, <hi>Who being in the form of God thought it no robbery to equal with God; but made himſelf of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſs of men,</hi> &amp;c. though he were a creature as he was Man, yet he is true God Creator; as he is God, he is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtower of the ſame gifts, as God the Father, and he together with God the Father, doth inable people to leave their ſins, and to walk in his ways; this we may ſee, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.23. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> compared, where ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, the fulneſs of him that filleth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154197:9"/> all in all; and <hi>You hath he quickned, who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, wherein in time paſt ye walked, according to the courſe of this World,</hi> &amp;c. Chriſt inables the Saints to make progreſs in holineſs, to proceed in every good Word and Work.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He directs us what courſe to take, that we might obtain bleſſings from God; namely from God.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>The way to obtain bleſſings from God, is to ſeek it of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Apoſtle prevents an objection which they might make; he exhorts them to ſtedfaſtneſs; but they might ſay,</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>How may we do to keep in the ways of God? whence ſhould we have this power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He Anſwers,</hi> We may have it from God, and from Jeſus Chriſt, as appears in the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt]</hi> He doth not ſay the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but our's; mark whom he ſpeaks it of, not only of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (<hi>Paul</hi> the believer, and <hi>Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi>) but the Saints, the believers of the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica:</hi> from hence obſerve this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>True faith doth apply Jeſus Ch<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as it's own portion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154197:9"/>
            <p>Pſal. 119.57. <hi>Thou art my portion oh Lord:</hi> And again, Pſal. 16.5. <hi>The Lord is the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine inheritance:</hi> Lam. 3.24. <hi>The Lord is my portion ſaith my ſoul, therefore will I hope in him.</hi> And ſo true Faith doth apply Jeſus Chriſt to the ſoul, as it's own portion: Therefore when <hi>Thomas</hi> (that ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered in his faith) came to confirm it, <hi>by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his hand into his ſide,</hi> &amp;c. he ſaith, <hi>My Lord and my God,</hi> Joh. 20. <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. To apply this then, You then that have Faith, prize it; as Chriſt is call'd Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſo likewiſe is Faith call'd Precious; it is precious Faith, by which you come to imbrace precious Chriſt; now as Chriſt is the gift of God, ſo Faith is the gift of God; and you cannot receive Jeſus Chriſt (who is the gift of God) but by Faith: <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>To as many as received him, he gave power to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe on his Name;</hi> Believing is receiving.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. Oh then labour for Faith, we can never go to Heaven without Faith; conſider what will it advantage you, that he is the Lord Jeſus, unleſs he be your Lord Jeſus? what profit is it to you t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e is a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, if he be not your Saviour? we have no ground of comfort, to hear of the Lord Jeſus <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iſt, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>till we believe in him, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>m; if we believe not, we m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> dye in <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſins: [<hi>Our Lord Jeſus,</hi> or our Saviour] <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>he word ſignifies) Our Saviour, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154197:10"/>
            <p>Doct. <hi>Chriſt is our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he is call'd often throughout the New Teſtament; Chriſt is our Saviour, and he alone; <hi>There's no other ſalvation to be had in any other,</hi> Acts 4.12.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt is our Saviour, as he ſaves us from Sathan, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>He led captivity captive;</hi> it is Chriſt that came to deſtroy the works of the Devil; and when he did come, he did conquer and overcome principalities and power, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. it's Jeſus Chriſt that recovers ſinners out of the ſnare of the Devil, that's the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He ſaves us from ſin, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Thou ſhal't call his name Jeſus,</hi> (ſaith the Angel) <hi>for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins.</hi> I might ſhew you both joyn'd together, in the 2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>And you hath he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in time paſt ye walked according to the courſe of this World, according to the Prince of the power of the air,</hi> &amp;c. Firſt he ſaves his people from the power of ſin, he ſets them into a glorious liberty, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.34, 36. (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>He that commits ſin, is the ſervant of ſin:</hi> and in the 36. <hi>verſ. If the Son make you free, you ſhall be free indeed:</hi> and (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11.) <hi>reckon your ſelves to be dead indeed unto ſin; but alive unto God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> 1 Pet. 1.18, 19. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154197:10"/> as ye know that you were not redeemed from your vain converſation with corruptible things, as Silver and Gold, but with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb without blemiſh.</hi> Secondly, Jeſus Chriſt ſaves (as from the power of ſin) ſo from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty due to ſin, from the puniſhment of ſin; as firſt from the curſe of the Law: <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for us,</hi> Gal. 3.13. ſecondly, from the wrath of God; 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Jeſus who delivereth us from the wrath to come;</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.8, 9, 10. <hi>For God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to obtain ſalvation through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Who died for us, that whether we wake or ſleep, we ſhould live together with him:</hi> it is he alone by whom we obtain ſalvation. Let us only apply it in a word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> How precious then ſhould Jeſus Chriſt be to us? ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you that believe (therefore) he is precious:</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>verſ.</hi> I! he is your Saviour, <hi>He that believeth on him ſhall not be confounded:</hi> Oh! how do captives love their Redeemer? when they ſee the man that comes to free them out of bondage, how do they love the ſight of him? Oh how ſhould ſinners love Jeſus Chriſt who is their Saviour! 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be anathama, Maranatha:</hi> Oh let it not for ſhame be ſaid, that we love not the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154197:11"/> Chriſt! Oh curſed is that man that loves not Jeſus Chriſt who comes to bring bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him! we ſhould love Jeſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is altogether lovely, <hi>white and ruddy, the chiefeſt among ten thouſand,</hi> Cant. 5.10. none can ſave us but he. Then again the conexion of the words is very remarkable, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth not ſay our Lord Chriſt himſelf, nor our Jeſus himſelf, but our Lord Jeſus: he joyns Lord and Jeſus both together; and what the Scripture joyns together, we muſt not put aſunder: from whence we may raiſe this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>They whoſe Jeſus is, he is their Lord:</hi> (or if you pleaſe thus) <hi>They to whom Chriſt is a Jeſus, he is a Lord:</hi> or, <hi>Whom Chriſt ſaves, them he rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom Chriſt is a Saviour, to them he is a Governour: Chriſt <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be our Jeſus, he is our Lord; if we miſtake here, we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done for ever: <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31 The Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jeſus Chriſt, he faith thus, <hi>Him hath God exalted to be a Prince and a Saviour,</hi> &amp;c. he hath exalted him to be a Prince and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>to give repentance to</hi> Iſrael, not only a Saviour but a Prince: they go both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, where Chriſt is a Saviour there he is a Prince: where Chriſt gives remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins, he giveth power over ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Sin ſhall not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154197:11"/> have dominion over you; for you are not under the Law but under grace:</hi> you that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſaving grace of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, you are ſet free from ſin; not but that you may fall into ſin, but it doth not bear ſway in your ſoul; it cannot have it's full command, you cannot be led captive to ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> Now this may be for a uſe of trial, to try whether Chriſt be our Saviour yea or no; examine your ſelves, be faithful to your own ſouls: would you know whether Chriſt be your Ieſus or no? ask your ſelves this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is he your Lord or no? is he your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour? he is the King of Saints, as well as the Saviour of his people: if you follow your luſts, and live in ſin knowingly, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly walk after the ſinful deſires of your own hearts, Chriſt will profit you nothing: you ſhall find what I ſay to be true one day, (I wiſh you find it not by ſad experience) if you will not be ſubject to the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, do not ſo much as expect mercy from Ieſus Chriſt: for Ieſus Chriſt tells you himſelf, if you will not be rul<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by him, he will not ſave you: if you will not obey his Goſpel, he will be a deſtroyer and not a Saviour to you: remember what he hath ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.27. if you refuſe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, look not for any favour from him: <hi>As for thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould reign over them, bring hither
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154197:12"/> and ſlay them before me.</hi> That man that would have his luſts reign, and not me rule over him; bring that ſoul before me, I will throw him into Hell: Many ſhall flatter themſelves, (as in that 13. of <hi>Luk.</hi> 25. and come with confidence, ſaying <hi>Lord, Lord, open unto us,</hi> &amp;c. let us go into Heaven, but he ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Lord? why call you me Lord? I know you not, whence ye are; but then they ſhall begin to make apology, and ſay, we have heard thou art a Jeſus, we have eaten and drunk in thy preſence, we have been at thy Ordinances, at thy Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; thou haſt taught in our ſtreets; but he ſhall ſay, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>I tell you I know you not,</hi> you are ſtrangers to me, I never remember you kept my commands. I tell you I will not take notice of you, <hi>depart from me all ye work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of iniquity;</hi> if you will not take one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, there's a ſecond, <hi>depart from me all ye workers of iniquity;</hi> Oh how ſad will it be then! therefore now take the adviſe of our Saviour, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtraight gate, for many ſhall ſeek to enter, but ſhall not be able.</hi> Chriſt will ſave only thoſe that obey him; therefore I beſeech you let me put this queſtion to you, (for I would fain not have you go to Hell) pray ask your own hearts alone, in ſecret, is there no known ſin committed? is there no known ſin I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in? if thy heart make known to thee that there is, if thou wilt not leave this ſin,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154197:12"/> it is a ſign that Chriſt is none of thine: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>The Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſin,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe that Chriſt ſaves, he hath ſaid. <hi>Sin ſhall not have dominion over them: Paul</hi> that great admirer of Ieſus Chriſt, he tells the people plainly (that they may not flatter themſelves) <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt,</hi> and leaſt they ſhould miſtake, (he ſaith) <hi>that walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. who though they have their ſins, and their fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yet their deſire is to walk not after the luſts of their Hearts, but after the Spirit: for, for all Chriſt died for ſinners, yet if they live and dye in their ſins, Chriſt will not ſave them: <hi>if we live after the fleſh we ſhall dye,</hi> Rom. 8.13. and though it be true, and this be a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners;</hi> yet know this on the other hand, Jeſus Chriſt did never intend to ſave thoſe that remain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent, hard-hearted, and ſtubborn ſinners: that live and dye in wickedneſs, they ſhall find no mercy: <hi>Job</hi> profeſſeth his Faith in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, yet if he were not his Lord and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, woe to him: the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.11. ſaith, <hi>Woe to the wicked, it ſhall be ill with him; for the reward of his hands it ſhall be given him:</hi> remember this, We ſhall as ſurely go to Hell for all Chriſt dyed, as if he had never dyed, if we live and dye in ſin: therefore, if thou
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154197:13"/> wouldeſt have Chriſt a Saviour, make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of obeying Chriſt: <hi>Bleſſed are the unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, in the way,</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1. <hi>who walk in the Law of the Lord.</hi> ver. 8. <hi>I will keep thy ſtatutes, oh forſake me not utterly.</hi> If thou wil't keep Gods ſtatutes, thou mayeſt expect to be kept ſafe; and <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Thy word have I hid in my heart, that I might not ſin againſt thee:</hi> I, then may we hope to do well: <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>I have choſen the way of truth, thy judgments have I laid before me:</hi> ver. 31. <hi>I have ſtuck unto thy teſtimonies: Oh Lord put me not to ſhame:</hi> and again, <hi>ver.</hi> 101. <hi>I have refrained my feet from every evil way, that I might keep thy word:</hi> 102. <hi>I have not departed from thy judgments, for thou haſt taught me:</hi> ver. 162. <hi>I rejoyce in thy word, as one that findeth great ſpoyles:</hi> ver. 163. <hi>I hate und ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor lying, but thy law do I love:</hi> ver. 166. <hi>Lord, I have hoped for thy ſalvation, and done thy commandments.</hi> Then indeed if we make it our buſineſs, deſign and endeavour, to keep the commandments of Chriſt, we may then hope to ſee the ſalvation of God; then and not till then: 2 <hi>Titus</hi> 11. <hi>For the grace of God that bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared:</hi> ver. 12. (mark) <hi>Teaching us to deny ungodlyneſs and worldly luſts, and that we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world:</hi> ver. 13. <hi>Looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ver. 14. <hi>Who gave himſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154197:13"/> for us, that he might redeem us from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and purifie unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works.</hi> Now this is as well the command of Chriſt, that they make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their duty to him, as well as to look for ſalvation from him; therefore if you would have Chriſt for your Jeſus, be ſure that he be your Lord, that you do him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; obſerve his Laws, and reverence his Name, (not by bowing at the name Jeſus) bowing is a note of ſubjection, and ſheweth, that all creatures are ſubject to Jeſus Chriſt; unto the authority of Chriſt, have reſpect to all his commands: if people will not, but walk after their luſts, will do wickedly: remember this, that inſtead of ſalvation, you muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect (or how ever you will find) deſtruction, and perdition, as it's call'd, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the wicked he ſhall rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible tempeſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For God is angry with the wicked every day,</hi> Pſal. 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. Chriſt hath plainly told peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he will be no Saviour to them that refuſe obedience to him; <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41. Chriſt tells you what he will do, <hi>The Son of man ſhall ſend forth his Angels and they ſhall gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, and them which do iniquity; and ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fire, &amp;c.</hi> Oh that ſinners would believe, what they ſhall one day feel; that they would now fear and tremble, that they may then be delivered from wrath to come:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154197:14"/> therefore though thy ſins be never ſo pleaſing and delightful to thee, caſt it from thee, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.43. <hi>It is better for thee to enter into life maimed then to bo caſt into Hell,</hi> &amp;c. Oh let us be wiſe for our ſalvation, willing to part with our moſt pleaſing ſins, rather then to have our ſouls deſtroyed, and caſt into Hell; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting burnings: think not that Jeſus Chriſt will ſave you, unleſs you turn from ſin; and therefore pray earneſtly that you may be converted, and have your ſins blotted out, the 73. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. Oh let this be our earneſt prayer, <hi>That we may be guided by Gods counſel,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt may be ours: <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.6 <hi>Thine they were and thou gaveſt them me, and they have kept my word;</hi> then may you be ſure he hath promiſed and prayed for you, <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 24. <hi>Father I will that thoſe whom thou haſt given me,</hi> thoſe that have kept my word, <hi>may be where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou haſt given me,</hi> &amp;c. If Chriſt be our Lord, he will be our Jeſus, but not elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, who hath loved us, and hath given us everlaſting conſolation and good hope through grace, comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:154197:14"/>
            <head>Afternoon Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>The 2 of the</hi> Theſſalonians <hi>2. Cap. 16, 17. Verſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father which hath loved us, and hath given us everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17.</hi> Comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU may Remember, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we took notice of four things: firſt the Perſons praying, <hi>Paul, Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus:</hi> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Perſons prayed for, &amp;c. thirdly the Perſons prayed to; and that's firſt <hi>God the Son;</hi> and ſecondly <hi>God the Father,</hi> whoſe love we have firſt aſſerted, and ſecondly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: fourthly the bleſſings prayed for; and the firſt is <hi>Conſolation,</hi> ſecondly <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:154197:15"/>
            <p>We made entrance on the firſt Perſon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, <hi>[Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt]</hi> not the Lord Jeſus, but our Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Doct. I. <hi>Faith applies Jeſus Chriſt to it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. II. Again, <hi>Chriſt is our Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from the connexion <hi>[Our Lord Jeſus]</hi> we noted, that,</p>
            <p>Doct. III. <hi>To whom Chriſt is a Jeſus, to them he is a Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whom Chriſt ſaves, them he Rules.</p>
            <p>To proceed <hi>[and God even our Father]</hi> God is often call'd, as here, ſo in other places, frequently our Father; not only of <hi>Paul, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus;</hi> but yours and ours together: you that are Saints, thence note this point,</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>God is the Father of the righteous;</hi> or, <hi>He is the Father of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is the Father of all that are truly religious Perſons, of all the Diſciples of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Chriſt after his reſurrection, in 20. of <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. ſaith to <hi>Mary,</hi> go to my Brethren and ſay, <hi>I aſcend to my Father and to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154197:15"/> your Father:</hi> the Father of our Lord Jeſus, and our Father.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But how ſhall I know whether God be my Father or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By theſe two marks, or ſigns; by our Repentance, and by our Faith.</p>
            <p>God is the Father of repenting, believing, ſinners; though he be the Father of all, in reſpect of creation, and common mercies; yet God is only the Father (through Ieſus Chriſt) of thoſe that repent, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Come out from amongſt them, and be you ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch none unclean thing.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And I will be a Father unto you, and you ſhall be my ſons and daughters, ſaith the Lord God Almighty:</hi> They that leave their ſins, and cleave to God with full purpoſe of heart, have juſt ground to call God Father. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, To them that believe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>To as many as received him, he gave power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sons of God, even to as many as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on his name.</hi> Gal. 3.26. ver. <hi>For ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> thou that haſt an heart to repent of ſins, and to believe in the Lord Ieſus, may'ſt have comfort, to go to God as thy Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. But to apply this, if this be ſo, then we may ſee, firſt the Saints dignity, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.23. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of this as a great privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that he was related to the King, and what do you take no notice of it? ſeemeth it a ſmall thing to you that I call the King Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154197:16"/> Oh then, what priviledge is it to be the adopted Sons and Daughters of the King of Kings.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We may ſee the Saints ſafety; conſider what God is; and then we ſhall ſee what cauſe of comfort they have that are Gods people.</p>
            <p>Conſider firſt, he is of great power, <hi>Job</hi> 42.2. <hi>ver.</hi> He can do any thing though never ſo difficult, nothing is too hard for the Lord; he is the mighty Potentate, he doth whatſoever he pleaſes: he is mighty in ſtrength, who hath hardened himſelf againſt him and proſpered? He can bind mens hands, and rule mens hearts, and do what ever he will: <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>He is able to do exceeding abundantly above what we can ask or think:</hi> who is ſo great a God as our God? we that fear him: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.13, 14. <hi>Thy way oh God is in the ſanctuary: who is ſo great a God as our God?</hi> thou art the God that doſt wonders, thou haſt declared thy ſtrength among the people: <hi>Job</hi> 11.7. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching find out God? canſt thou find out the Almighty unto perfection?</hi> Here's thy priviledge, if thou have the work of grace wrought in thee, here's thy ſafety, God is thy Father, that God that never wants power, to defend his people, that is ſeen in the mount, and will not many times help, till we are in extreamity, that his power may then be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; ſafe they are that have God for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he is ſufficient to protect them.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154197:16"/>
            <p>Conſider ſecondly, God is very wiſe; a wiſe Father, and that in regard of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and in regard of his prudence; he knoweth what ever men do in the World, <hi>Job</hi> 34.21. <hi>For his eyes are upon the ways of man, and he ſeeth all his goings.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>Ther's no darkneſs, or ſhadow of death, where the workers of iniquity can hide themſelves:</hi> Iob 12.22. <hi>He diſcovereth deep things out of darkneſs, and bringeth out to light the ſhaddow of death.</hi> He knoweth men better then they know themſelves; God needeth none to give him intelligence, he knoweth what is done in the ſecret cloſet of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of our hearts: Nay, ſecondly he is very prudent too, he knoweth how to order his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; he is wiſe in heart (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>): that man is wiſe indeed, that knows how to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit the wiſeſt of men: God knoweth how to enſnare the wicked in the works of their own hands, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.25. <hi>That fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the tokens of the liars, and maketh the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners mad, that turneth wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh.</hi> Come on (ſaith <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) let us deal wiſely; but he was out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted: <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.28. <hi>God turns the counſel of</hi> Achitophel <hi>into fooliſhneſs:</hi> God is never at a loſs, he knows what to do.</p>
            <p>Conſider thirdly, He is a very tender Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too; he is very pittiful, very merciful, a very tender Father, that lays to heart the miſeries of his people; when they were in <hi>Egypt</hi> he pittied them; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. <hi>In all their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154197:17"/> afflictions he was afflicted, and the angel ef his preſence ſaved them,</hi> &amp;c. (ſpeaking after the manner of men) they that lay the troubles of others to heart as their own: and he is not thus pittiful only to his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but to all his people: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.13. <hi>Like as a Father pittieth his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo doth the Lord pitty thoſe that fear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, Conſider fourthly, He is a very careful Father, he minds how it goes with his children: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Caſt all your care upon him,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>for he careth for you:</hi> you are never out of his eye or thoughts; when <hi>Zion</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord hath forſaken me, and my God hath forgotten me;</hi> Iſa. 49.14, 15. (ſaith God) <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb? yea they may forget, yet will not I forget thee,</hi> &amp;c. The condition, and troubles, and miſeries thou art in, are always in my thoughts: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.18. <hi>The needy ſhall not always be forgotten: the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the poor ſhall not periſh for ever:</hi> That's the ſecond, but</p>
            <p>Uſe III. Hence we may learn our Duty, <hi>(If God be the Saints Father)</hi> and what's that?</p>
            <p>Firſt duty, To pray to him: whom ſhould they go to but to their Faither; <hi>Be careful for nothing</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but in every thing let your requeſt be made known to him, by prayer and ſupplication:</hi> Phil. 4.6. <hi>and</hi> Mat. 7.24. Pſal. 145.18. ver. <hi>The Lord is nigh unto all that cal upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154197:17"/>
            <p>Second duty, Truſt in him; whom ſhould we truſt, if not our Father? therefore truſt in him; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.3. <hi>Put not your truſt in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor in the ſon of man, in whom there is none help:</hi> ver. 5. <hi>Happy is he that hath the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God:</hi> The Scripture denounceth a woful curſe to him that truſteth in any thing but in God; <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm;</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is:</hi> God takes notice of thoſe that truſt in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.17. <hi>An horſe is a vain thing for ſafety; neither ſhall he deliver any by his great ſtrength:</hi> So long as we truſt to our ſelves, at any time, for any thing, our caſe is ſad; but none that truſted in the Lord, have any cauſe ever to be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us Honour him (if a Father) and that in three reſpects: firſt in our thoughts; have always good thoughts of God, what ever his providences be towards us; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.17. <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his ways, &amp;c.</hi> what ever God doth is good, he is juſt, he is righteous in all thoſe ways, that are moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil'd at by men; <hi>Job</hi> 34.21. He will not lay upon man more then is right; everyman may ſay in the bittereſt croſs in the World, God hath not dealt with me after my ſins, it's a mercy we are on this ſide Hell. Secondly, Honour God, as in our thoughts, ſo in our words; ſpeak well of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.1. <hi>Give
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154197:18"/> thanks unto the Lord for he is good, for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endureth for ever.</hi> Pſal. 146.1, 2. ver. <hi>Praiſe the Lord oh my ſoul, while I live will I praiſe the Lord: I will ſing praiſes to God while I have a being.</hi> Now praiſing God is honouring of him: <hi>He that offers me praiſe, glorifieth me:</hi> Pſal. 50.23. Thirdly, Honour him in all our ways: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Whether ye eat or drink, whatſoever ye do, do all to the glory of God:</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven:</hi> Phil. 1.11. <hi>Being filled with the fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which are by Jeſus Chriſt, unto the glory of God:</hi> Be very obedient, obey him willingly, conſtantly, univerſally, in all his commands, becauſe he is our Father. Laſtly, We that profeſs our ſelves to be Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: be like him, <hi>Be ye merciful as he is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful; holy as he is holy:</hi> But to go on: <hi>[Who hath loved us]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>God loves his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſal. 145.8. ver. Pſal. 147.10, 11. <hi>The Lord loves his Saints;</hi> Love! I here's love indeed: 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Behold what manner of love is here, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God:</hi> And if this be ſo,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> Then bleſs him for his love; thank him for it: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1. <hi>Bleſs the Lord oh my ſoul, and all that is within me, praiſe his holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:154197:18"/>
            <p>And that in this reſpect, Firſt, God loves us undeſerved, and that in two reſpects; firſt, before we loved him: 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.10, 19. <hi>Herein is love, in that he loved us firſt:</hi> and ſecondly, God loves us, as before we loved him, ſo when we had nothing to render us lovely to him: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. While we were ſinners, ungodly, in our wickedneſs, when we had nothing but ſin and corruption in us; not that he loved his peoples ſins, but their perſons: when the whole head was ſick, and the whole heart faint, nothing but ſores and putrifying corruptions; yet he loved his people though he hated their corruptions; he loved them, and loved them before they had grace. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. <hi>ver. Having predeſtinated us unto the adoption of children by Jeſus Chriſt to himſelf, according to the good pleaſure of his will: To the praiſe of the glory of his grace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As God loved us undeſervedly, ſo conſtantly: Jeſus Chriſt having loved his own, he loves them to the end: A friend loves at all times (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) in time of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, as well as proſperity; there are few ſuch friends in the World, but God is ſuch a friend; he loves his people, when others care not for them: God will love you that are his people, always, at all times; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>The mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee; neither ſhall the covenant of my peace be removed, ſaith the Lord, that hath mercy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154197:19"/> on thee.</hi> He hath taken you into an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing covenant with him; and elſe where they are call'd everlaſting hills, becauſe they laſt as long as the World laſteth: but there will come a time, when they ſhall be broken, and the Earth ſhall be no more: Oh but his love is everlaſting, when time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. Secondly, If this be ſo, then let them that have grace, take heed of offending God: a wiſe man will be willing to pleaſe, and loth to diſpleaſe ſuch a Father as he is; take heed of doing evil in the ſight of God, ſtand in awe and ſin not; for all iniquity is abomination in the ſight of God; God loves you, oh do not provoke him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III. Again thirdly, Doth God love his people? then let us love them that fear God and walk in his ways: <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Be followers of God, as dear children:</hi> God loves the righteous.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Hereby we ſhall reſemble God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Hereby we evidence our love to God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Hereby you will evidence Gods love to you, if you love thoſe that are Gods: 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3, 14. <hi>We know we are paſſed from death to life, be <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we love the Brethren:</hi> and 18.19. verſ. <hi>Let us not love only in word but in deed and in truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> IV. Fourthly, Doth God love his people? then let us not be troubled, though
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154197:19"/> the World hate us, what though men regard us not, remember this, if thou feareſt God, God loves thee, rejoyce in this oh Saints! thou that art the ſervants of God, though thou art not the favourite of great men, thou art the favourite of the great God. <hi>[And hath given us everlaſting conſolation] Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting conſolation,</hi> that is everlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; everlaſting life: it is therefore call'd everlaſting conſolation, becauſe the happineſs of mans life, is the comfort of his life: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in Scripture and conſolation, is taken for happineſs. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn for they ſhall be comforted:</hi> Mat. 5.4. That is, they ſhall be brought into that glorious hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25. <hi>Son remember, that thou in thy life time, receiveſt thy good things, and</hi> Lazarus <hi>evil things, but now he is comforted and thou art tormented: He is comforted,</hi> that is, he is made bleſſed, as appears in the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the words, <hi>but thou art tormented;</hi> Luk. 6.21. <hi>Bleſſed are you that weep, but you ſhall laugh:</hi> it is not taken in that ſenſe, we commonly take laughing in; but ye ſhall be made happy, that is the meaning: and ſo <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 24. <hi>Woe to you that are rich now, for you have received your conſolation:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are rich in ſelf conceit, in prid<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vain glory, that boaſt in the multitud<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of your riches, you have received your conſolation; (as if he ſhould ſay) you have all the happineſs you are like to have; they ſhall have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154197:20"/> no more: From whence this Point,</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>God hath given his people everlaſting happineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God hath given it them in the promiſe of the Word: <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Fear not little flock, it is your Fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom:</hi> and ere long they ſhall have the performance of it, God is giving everlaſting conſolation, it is not long ere thou ſhalt receive it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> And if it be ſo, then be not dejected at ſhort tribulation, and the troubles you meet with in the World, why? though you be afflicted for a moment, <hi>Yet the rod ſhall not always lye upon the back of the righteous,</hi> Pſal. 125. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5. <hi>They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy:</hi> Pſal. 30.5. <hi>Weeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> the night of this World may be a night of affliction, but in the morning we ſhall have joy and comfort; <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Let not your hearts be troubled</hi> (ſaith our Saviour); and we know ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>When this earthly tabernacle ſhall be diſſolved, we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands,</hi> &amp;c. as ſoon as you dye, your trouble ſhall end, and your joy then begins; and then no man ſhall be able to take that joy from you; <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.22. <hi>God will hide his face from you no more;</hi> Iſa. 54.7. <hi>For a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154197:20"/> moment have I hid my face from thee, but with great Mercies will I gather thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[And good hope through grace]</hi> this is taken two waies,</p>
            <p>Doct. I. <hi>As God gives his people ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs, ſo he gives them hope of it.</hi> Rom. 15. verſ. 13.</p>
            <p>He is call'd the God of hope: as the object of our hope, ſo the Author of it,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Good hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do. II. <hi>The Saints hope of happineſs is a good hope:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good in the riſe of it, the work of God: in the nature of it; the work of the Spirit: in the end of it; it makes People good, therefore let us all labour for it,</p>
            <p>Doct. III. <hi>The ground of Peoples hope of Everlaſting happineſs, is meerly through the grace of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saints everlaſting happineſs, is from the free grace of God. Rom. 6.23. <hi>The gift of God is eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord</hi> Ephe. 2.8. <hi>For by grace are ye ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God.</hi> And if it be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> Why then I mighty ſhew you, it is not from man's deſerving, that he hath happineſs,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154197:21"/> man cannot merit Heaven, it is not from the deſert of man; for mans merit, and God's free grace, are quite oppoſite, one to another. I ſhould have ſhow'n the folly of that opinion, that hold men may merit happineſs from God.</p>
            <p>For Firſt they muſt do that which is good.</p>
            <p>And Secondly that only.</p>
            <p>And Thirdly by his own ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, more then he ought to do.</p>
            <p>And Fifthly, the works muſt be Proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the happineſs he expects.</p>
            <p>But Firſt, no man can do good, for we are born evil. Secondly, not only good, for in many things we offend all. Thirdly, we are not ſufficient of our ſelves. Fourthly, if we could do what we ſhould, yet not more then we are bound: for we have but done our duty <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.7.8.9.10. Read it at your lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; doth the Maſter thank is ſervant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I trow not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fiftly, if he could do more then God requires of him, his work could never be ſo good as to call for ſuch a reward of everlaſting happineſs: ther's no Proportion, between the little good we Creatures can do, and that happineſs God hath laid up, for them that fear him: it is an Opinion that hath neither Religion, nor reaſon, in it, and ſuch as ſome of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Comfort your hearts]</hi> whereas the Apoſtle
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154197:21"/> prays for theſe bleſſings, we may obſerve this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>God's people, have need of Comfort in this World, as well as grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay not as much need; miſtake me not: not ſo much need, and that in two reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they may ſerve God without Comfort, but cannot ſerve him without grace: they may ſerve God, though God hide his face, and thereby excerciſing their patience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they have not ſo much need; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may be ſaved, without Comfort, but they cannot without grace: it is not ſaid, the Mourners ſhall be deſtroyed, but the Tranſgreſſours. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>verſ.</hi> 38. <hi>Without Holyneſs none ſhall ſee the Lord:</hi> but he ſaith not, without Comfort none ſhall ſee God: it is poſſible, though not uſual, for a Child of God, to live and die without comfort, that is; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manifeſtation, of the love of God to him; God may hide his face from him all his daies: <hi>Heman</hi> complains, that holy and wiſe man, that he had been afflicted, with terrors from his youth: and ſo <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> how long lay they under afflictions, without comfort.</p>
            <p>Saith one that was upon his Death-bed, and could find no Comfort: did you ever read of any one that upon his Death-bed had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort (if he were the Child of God) that God
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154197:22"/> hid his face from? and he was anſwered, yes: ſaith he, one he had, and that was the Son of God himſelf, who, when he was ready to give up the Ghoſt cried out, my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</p>
            <p>But they have need of comfort, in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; firſt, becauſe they will have much trouble in the world <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. <hi>Many are the troubles of the Righteous;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we were of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.11.12. <hi>And all that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer Perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, without comfort, their hearts will be ready to fail them: Gods peoples natural ſtrength is but like to that of other mens: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they have not ſtrength given them from above, (having more troubles then others) they were never able to bear up. <hi>Joh</hi> 16.33. when Chriſt tells them he is going out of the world, he gives them a Cordial before hand to prevent their fainting: <hi>In the World you ſhall have trouble, but be of good cheer, I have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the World:</hi> and in the, 14. 15. 16. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſeveral Cordials which he gave them, to ſupport their hearts, as ſeeing he left them in a troubleſome World: and therefore he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth them; that when he was gone he would ſend them a comforter. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16. <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, even the Spirit of Truth,</hi> &amp;c. the Second Doctrine, from hence, in that he prays
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154197:22"/> that God would Comfort their hearts, is this:</p>
            <p>Doct. II. <hi>Chriſtians in time of trouble ought to pray to God to comfort them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> I. And that Firſt, becauſe none elſe can comfort them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> II. Secondly, becauſe God hath comforted his People, when they have been in trouble: my fleſh and my heart faileth, but God is the ſtrength of my heart and my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.17. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the Lord had been mine help, my ſoul had, long ſince dwell't in ſilence.</hi> and verſ. 18. 19. 22. <hi>when I ſaid my foot ſlippeth, thy mercy oh Lord, held me up in the multitude of my thoughts within me thy comforts refreſh my ſoule, but the Lord is my defence: and my God is the Rock of my refuge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> III. Thirdly, pray to God for comfort, for as he hath comforted his people in the old, ſo in the new Teſtament, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; the Father of mercies, and the God of all Comfort,</hi> ver. 4. 5. <hi>who comforteth us in all our Tribulations, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble, with the ſame Comforts, wherewith we our ſelves are comforted of God; for as the ſufferings of Chriſt abound in us, ſo our Conſolation alſo aboundeth by Chriſt.</hi> And again, God hath promiſed, he will ſtill comfort his people: he will ſuite comforts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154197:23"/> to the troubles his people are in. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.13. <hi>As one whom his Mother Comforteth, ſo will I comfort you,</hi> &amp;c. as a tender Parent her Child, if but little faith, weak in grace; God will comfort his according to their trouble. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.18. <hi>I will not leave you Orphans,</hi> (ſo the word ſignifies) now that we may have comfort in trouble, let us repent thoſe ſins that are the cauſe of our trouble, he that confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſins ſhall have mercy: God doth not willingly afflict his people, let us therefore be humbled for our ſins, and for the ſins of others: for the ſins of the Nation, for our <hi>Sodome</hi> ſins: Pride, Idlneſs, and fullneſs of Bread: let's be humbled, for our earthly mindedneſs, luxury, carnal ſecurity, for our not priſing the Goſpel, abuſing the Goſpel, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the grace of God into wantonneſs; let us be humbled, for our own ſins, [the ſins of our Relations, of our families: that we have not loved the Simplicity of the Goſpel, that we, could not indure plain powerfull Practical Preaching of the Word, if not curiouſly Cook't, and finely dreſt, the food of our Souls would not down with us; Oh! let us be humbled for all our ſins that is the way to have comfort, take the Councel of the Apoſtle <hi>James: Humble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord, and he ſhall lift you up. Jam.</hi> 4. <hi>ver</hi> 10. and then we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect theſe three Cordials; to comfort us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God will be with us in all our troubles.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God will do us good by them.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:154197:23"/>
            <p>And laſtly, he will bring us out of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if we humble, and repent us of our ſins, God will be with us, in our troubles; who ever thou art, and what condition ſoever thou art in. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> God will be with his People, underneath ſhall be his everlaſting arms: God was with his People of Old in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the Wilderneſs, in Captivity: he was with <hi>Daniel,</hi> in the Den; with <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> in the Stocks; with <hi>Peter,</hi> in Priſon, with <hi>John,</hi> in <hi>Pathmos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God will do us good by our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>All things ſhall work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good to thoſe that love God,</hi> &amp;c. and in very faithfullneſs thou haſt afflicted me, (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) and it is good for me that I have been afflicted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and who can harme you if you do well; ſaith <hi>Paul;</hi> God will draw us off from ſin, by it, make us meet to be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Heaven; our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal weight of glory.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God will in due time, bring you out of trouble, God will not alwaies leave his People in trouble: <hi>the Rod of the wicked ſhall not alwaies reſt upon the back of the righteous:</hi> and <hi>Pſal,</hi> 34.4. <hi>I ſought the Lord, and he heard
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154197:24"/> me and delivered me,</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>The Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous cry: and the Lord heareth; and delivereth them out of all their troubles;</hi> Oh let's labour to have an humble Spirit! to be affected with and humbled for our ſins; and a praying Spirit, and God will deliver us: waite but for a time, <hi>&amp;c. It is good for a man to waite and quietly to hope for the Salvation of the Lord. Lam.</hi> 3.26. For God will not ſuffer us to be tempted, above what we are able: but will make away to eſcape. But to go on. <hi>[And ſtabliſh you]</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>Chriſtians ſhould labour to be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in every good word, let your ſpeech be alwaies ſeaſoned with grace: our diſcourſes ſhould never be frothy but Savory. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3.4. <hi>Fooliſhnes, and filthy talking let it no be once named,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: and (by the way) take heed of deriding Scripture, of jeſting with Scripture Phraſes: but the meaning of the words is, that you may be ſtabliſhed in the Truth of the Goſpel; that is in all Doctrinal and Practical truths: the meaning is, I pray (ſaith the Apoſtle) that you be not led a ſide, by the errour of the wicked, either in regard of unſound Opinions, or unholy converſation; hold faſt the form of ſound words, walk in the truth, with well doing; buy the truth and ſell it not: labour to be ſound in God's ſtatutes in regard of your judgment, and ſincere in your
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154197:24"/> practices. I ſhould have given you many Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to preſs you to this duty of ſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motive</hi> I. This will be to the honour of God, and make the world believe, that God is in this People of a truth: certainely, ther's a God in Heaven, that makes his People on Earth to be ſteadfaſt in their ſervice of God: that they will not turn aſide from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motive</hi> II. Again, this will be the joy, of Miniſters here and hereafter, 3. <hi>Epiſtle of Job. ver.</hi> 4. <hi>I have no greater joy, then to hear that my Children walk in truth:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, of theſe <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that their ſteadfaſtneſs did comfort him in all his afflictions. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7.8.9. <hi>Therefore my Brethren, we were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted over you, in all our afflictions, and diſtreſs, by your faith: for now we live, if ye ſtand faſt in the Lord: for what, thanks can we render to God again for you, for all the joy, wherewith we joy, for your ſakes before our God:</hi> I this will rejoyce our hearts indeed, if you hold faſt: ſtand faſt, and we cannot tell how to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enough to God for it: oh; what a joy is this that God hath honoured us ſo far, that the word of God in our mouths, was not in vaine; but that People continue in the truth: and, ſo it will be, the Miniſters joy hereafter: 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19.20. <hi>For what is our hope, or joy or Crown
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154197:25"/> of rejoycing? are not even ye in the preſence of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, at his coming? for ye are our glory and joy.</hi> There will be the glory of Miniſters, when they come before the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Chriſt: when they can ſay, Lord here am I, and the Children thou haſt given me; and then to conclude with that, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Therefore, my brethren, dearly beloved, and longed for, my joy and Crown, ſo ſtand faſt in the Lord, my dearly beloved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motive</hi> III. And laſtly, this will be for your comfort, in this World, and in another world: by this you will make your calling and election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. <hi>And ſo an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance ſhall be Miniſtred unto you abundantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. and that you may be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Means</hi> I. Firſt, labour to converſe much in the Scriptures, do but as they direct you and you will not do a miſs, this was the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Bareans:</hi> they were called Noble, becauſe they ſearched the Scriptures; moſt People erre from the truth not knowing the Scriptures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. <hi>Therefore if you would not walk in the Counſel of the ungodly, not ſtand in the way of ſinners, nor ſit in the ſeat of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, let your delight be to meditate in the Law of the Lord.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Beloved, believe not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſpirit, but trie the Spirits, whether they be of God:</hi> trie them, how? Trie all Doctrines<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:154197:25"/> bring them to the Touchſtone, to the word; take no Opinion upon truſt: weigh Opinions in the balance of the Sanctuary; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the law, and to the Teſtimony</hi> &amp;c. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>We have a more ſure word of Propheſie, whereunto you do well to take heed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Means</hi> II. Secondly, if we would be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: let us be very watchfull, and that the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe unſound Doctrines, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Practices are very ſuitable to our corrupt Natures; be watchfull that you may be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened in the waies of the Lord: take heed that you fall not from your own ſteadfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Means</hi> III. Thirdly, be earneſt with God in prayer: that he would ſtabliſh you, and that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon.</hi> I. Firſt, becauſe none can ſtabliſh you but God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Without me you can do nothing:</hi> there is ſo much unbelief remains in the heart of the beſt men in the World, that we ſhall ſoon depart from God, unleſs he keep us: therefore, we muſt watch our hearts: <hi>Now he that ſtabliſheth us with you, in Chriſt, and hath anointed us, is God:</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> II. Secondly, let's pray to him, for ſtabliſhing, becauſe he hath promiſed to ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154197:26"/> his People in every good <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord and work: though God's people my backſlide for a time, yet if they belong to God he will humble them, for their ſins, it ſhall coſt them dear, and as <hi>Paul</hi> prays for it, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.13. <hi>That they might be ſtabliſhed:</hi> ſo he tells them of God's promiſe. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good Work in you, will perform it untill the day of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.3.4. <hi>The Lord is faithful, who ſhall ſtabliſh you and keep you from evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Means</hi> IV. The laſt direction I ſhall give you, look to recompence of reward; (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.) that made <hi>Moſes,</hi> leave all the pleaſures of the World, the pleaſures of ſin which were but for a ſeaſon; look to that reward to them that keep cloſe to his commands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>For tht Lord God is a Sun and Shield: the Lord will give grace and glory: no good thing will he withhold, from thoſe that walk uprightly:</hi> now what would you have more? what can you deſire more? Walk but uprightly, God will never diſappoint you: you may believe him, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man, that endureth Temptation, for when he is tried, he ſhall receive the Crown of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him:</hi> I ſhall conclude all this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, with the Direction and Exhortation of the ſpirit of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. <hi>To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh, will I give to eat of the Tree of life,</hi> and <hi>verſ. the</hi> 10. <hi>Be faithfull to the death, and I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154197:26"/> will give thee a Crown of Life: Oh, take notice of the advice, given to the Church of</hi> Philadelphia: <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Hold faſt that thou haſt, that no man take thy Crown:</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Behold, I come quickly: and my reward is with me to give every man, according as his Work ſhall be: God will render to every man according to his Workes: Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>To them who, by patient continuance in well doing, ſeek for glory, honour, and immortality, eternal life;</hi> Eternal life, ſhould be the end of all our Preaching, and your hearing, ſo the Apoſtle: <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Brethren, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for</hi> Iſrael <hi>is, that they might be ſaved:</hi> this was the portion of Scripture I firſt took to diſcourſe upon, when I firſt came amongſt you: and the deſire of my Soul was, that your Soules ſhould be ſaved; and I deſire ſtill, that I, and my People may ſerve the Lord: and therefore I wiſh, the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all: and the Lord grant that they which love not grace may have grace wrought in their hearts: and that you that have grace, may grow in grace, more and more: I wiſh even your perfection: I dare not appeal unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 20. but this I pray: that your love may abound more and more, in knowledge and in all judgment: 1 <hi>Theſ,</hi> 5.23. <hi>And the very God of peace, ſanctifie you wholly, and I pray God, that your whole Spirit, Soul and Body, may be perſerved, blamleſs, unto the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Heb. 13.20
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154197:27"/> 21. <hi>and the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus that great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of the Sheep, through the blood of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting covenant: make you perfect in every good work, to do his will working in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, who hath loved us, and hath given us Everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace, comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and Work.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:27"/>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:154197:28"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Pet. 1. verſ. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wherein ye greatly rejoyce, though now for a ſeaſon (if need be) ye are in heavineſs through manifold Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THough many Saints have but a ſmall Portion in this World, yet there is alotted to them a goodly heritage in another world: though they are not filled with the good things of the earth, yet they are promiſed (which is better) the glory of Heaven though they have but a little in Poſſeſſion, yet they have much in reverſion, and though many of them be Poore many times as to the things they have in hand: ye they are very Rich as to what they have in hope. Theſe Saints to whom <hi>Peter</hi> Writes, were Pilgrims and Strangers here on Earth; ſcatttered up and down the World, they had no certaine abode, no continuing City, yet they ſoug<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> on that was to come, they looked for a City whoſe Builder and Maker was God; Silver and Gold; many of them either had none, or very little; and as to the Poſſeſſions of the Earth, their Portion was not great: Houſes and Lands
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154197:28"/> they were either denyed or deprived of, they ſuffered the Spoiling of their goods, yet they were begotten to a lively hope, unto an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance better then this world affords, unto an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled that fadeth not away; reſerved in Heaven for them and that they might know it was not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, for them but to be obtained by them the Apoſtle tells them, <hi>They ſhould be kept by the power of God through Faith unto Salvation;</hi> which now as it was promiſed them ſhould ere long be manifeſted, ready to be revealed in the laſt time, and the Apoſtle having ſhewed what they had hopes of, he ſhews what effect this their hope had upon them; namely much joy and Alacrity in the minds of their preſent Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Calamities; as the words I have read do declare unto you: <hi>Wherein ye greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which Verſe we may Obſerve,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Chriſtians great Joy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Chriſtians great Sorrow.</p>
            <p n="1">I. You have here believers great Joy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from hopes of their future Salvation, in theſe words, <hi>Wherein you greatly rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The Chriſtians or the Saints great Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ariſing from ſenſe of their preſent tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Ye are in heavyneſs through manifold tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Heavineſs, or which Temptations, are ſet forth</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:154197:29"/>
            <p>Firſt, By the time of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By the ground of them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. By the time of them, and that is declared in theſe words, <hi>Now for a ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. By the ground of them, and that is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed or intimated, <hi>If need be.</hi> Wherein you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein,</hi> that is in the hopes of Heaven, in the hopes of their inheritance, in the hopes of the glory of God, and that eternal Salvation that was promiſed to them, and expected by them; as the 4. and 5. <hi>verſes</hi> do declare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> you <hi>greatly rejoyce; you,</hi> though others do not, yet you rejoyce; others do not rejoyce in the hopes of Heaven, they have no right to it, no hope of it, they have no ground to expect it, it is not promiſed to them, nor no ground have they to look for it; but you that are the elect, the choſen, the called peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God; you that were as elected by the love, ſo ſanctified by the Spirit of God. 2. <hi>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein,</hi> that is in hopes of the glory of God, you rejoyce, you greatly rejoyce, you triumph for joy. Though now for a ſeaſon, or though now for a little time, you are in heavineſs, or in grief, through manyfold temptations, troubles and trials, you have in the World.</p>
            <p>The words are not difficult, they may afford us theſe ſix Inſtructions.</p>
            <p>From hence we might Obſerve, <hi>You are in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154197:29"/> heavineſs through manyfold temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the people of God in this world, are exerciſed with manyfold temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the Saints of the moſt high, or the people of the great God, and his peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are ſometimes in heavineſs through their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfold temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That the temptations true Chriſtians are exerciſed withall: ſhall be but for a ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>That there is need why God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſometimes ſhould be in this heavineſs, ſhould be exerciſed through manyfold temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>That when Gods people are in heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when they are exerciſed with manifold temptations there is need of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>That they that fear God ſhould rejoyce in hope of their eternal Salvation, though now they be in heavineſs through manyfold tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt and be but breif in it. You are in heavineſs through manyfold Temptations, manyfold temptations, it ſemes are your portion, the Doctrine that lies plain before us is this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That God's people in this World are often under many temptations.</hi> Many temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, or diverſe temptations as the word is elſewhere Tranſlated. <hi>James.</hi> 1. verſ. 2. <hi>Count it all joy when you fall into divers temptations.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:154197:30"/> In opening this truth I ſhall endeavour very breifly to anſwer theſe to Queries.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What is meant here by temptations?</p>
            <p>Secondly, How it may appeare that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are exerciſed, or annoyed by divers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, or manyfold temptations?</p>
            <p>Firſt, What we are to underſtand by temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> To that I anſwer this word temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is taken ſeveral ways in Scripture; but there are two Sorts of temptations that are eſpecially mentioned in the ſacred Word of God; there are temptations to evil, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations by evil; temptations are taken, either for an <hi>allurement</hi> unto Sinning, or for <hi>Chaſtiſement</hi> by ſuffering, either for temptations to <hi>Sin,</hi> or temptations to <hi>Sorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Temptations are taken ſometimes, for temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations unto <hi>Sin,</hi> ſo in Scripture often; to mention but ſome few places now, ſo we are to underſtand it in that place in that bleſſed form of Prayer (that may be well uſed if not abuſed as too often it is) <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.13. We are taught to pray, <hi>lead us not into temptation;</hi> that is, lead us not into temptation to <hi>Sin,</hi> and ſo the Apoſtles ſenſe is in what he ſaith. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. verſ. 9. <hi>They that will be rich, fall into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> they that are reſolved they will thrive, and proſper in the World whatever comes of it, which way ſoever they get it, they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>temptation,</hi> that is as the words following ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plane it, <hi>into a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:154197:30"/> hurtfull luſts which drown men in perdition, and deſtruction.</hi> Now in this ſenſe it is true the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have manifold temptations, the beſt of men are not ſometimes without the ſtrongeſt and greateſt temptations: temptations unto <hi>Sin,</hi> they are often tempted, by the <hi>Devil,</hi> and by the <hi>World,</hi> and by their own <hi>Hearts,</hi> to ſin, and that in ſeveral kinds, the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> the <hi>Practices</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> the <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tempted to caſt of the fear of God, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; ſo <hi>Job</hi> was, though he did not harken to, and was not overcome by that temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; but of theſe temptations it is not meant here.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As there are temptations to ſin, ſo there are temptations to ſorrow, as there are temptations to doing evil; ſo there are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in ſuffering of evil, and ſo temptations in Scripture are put for croſſes, and troubles, and afflictions that the godly meet with in the world, and St. <hi>Paul's</hi> troubles, amongſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the <hi>Jewes,</hi> are called his <hi>temptations,</hi> Acts. 20. verſ. 19. <hi>Serving the Lord with all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mind, and with many teares and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which befel me by the laying in wait of the</hi> Jewes. Many troubles that he met with through that croſs and perverſe People that he Preached often unto, and ſo the Exhortation of the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> is to be underſtood, <hi>James.</hi> 1. verſ. 2. <hi>My brethen count it all joy when you fall into divers temptations,</hi> that is, not when you are tempted to many ſins, but when you are
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154197:31"/> afflicted through many troubles; though you meet with many croſſes in the world, yet do not be troubled, but rejoyce, at it is, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endures temptation:</hi> that is bleſſed is the man, happy is the perſon that endures Perſecutions, afflictions for <hi>godlineſs</hi> ſake, for the <hi>Goſpels</hi> ſake, that is willing to <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> hath a heart to ſuffer, and ſtrength to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, in the ways, and ſervice of God, and ſo the time of <hi>temptation</hi> in this ſenſe is taken for trouble, for the time of Perſecution, for the time of affliction, and ſo our Saviour opens this Phraſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Luke.</hi> 8.13. <hi>verſ.</hi> compare it with <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20.21. <hi>verſ.</hi> what in the former place in <hi>Luke,</hi> is called temptation in <hi>Matthew;</hi> is called Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and Tribulation; what one ſaith when temptation comes, the other calls it Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Perſecution ariſes, by and by he is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and ſo we are to underſtand temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here in the Text, manyfold temptations, that is, manyfold afflictions, variety of troubles, and Calamities, all ſorts of croſſes which are therefore here called by the name <hi>temptation,</hi> becauſe men are tempted or tried by them, they try mens faith, and love, and obedience; they diſcover their ſincerity, and integrity. So much for the firſt here, what is meant by temptation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, How it doth appeare that the godly are exerciſed with manifold temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? This I might ſhew by an Induction of particulars, by teſtimony of Scripture, and by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154197:31"/> inſtances in the ſeveral ſorts of temptations, or troubles that the godly are afflicted with in this World.: I will ſpeak to one or two; take one Teſtimony of Scripture for it a few places I ſhall mention, Pſal. 34.19. <hi>Many are the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the Righteous.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.8. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide,</hi> Pſal. 88.3. <hi>My ſoul is full of troubles,</hi> Pſal. 25.17. <hi>The troubles of my heart are inlarged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as ever men begin to be good, to lead good lives they are apt to ſee bad days in ſome ſenſes. Heb. 10.32. <hi>After you were illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated you endured a great fight of afflictions.</hi> After you were brought to the ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God troubles were, preſently your Portion, the croſs is the conſtant companion of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I might ſhew further from whence it is, from the malice of the Devil, the rage of wicked men, the ſins of our own hearts, the wiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, the merciful providence of the good God towards his people, they have troubles and temptations in all kinds, of out ward man, of inward man, in friends, in enemies, in their perſons, in their relations, poſſeſſions, what ever they have that is neare and deare to them; but I cannot ſtand on <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iculars, let me only mention one, that <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e temptation that the Text mentions, and that is the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations that happen to the Saints here through Perſecution, for thoſe whom the Apoſtle writes to 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. they were ſcattered throughout
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154197:32"/> 
               <hi>Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynia,</hi> driven up and down for the Goſpels ſake, to ſave themſelves from the hand of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, and amongſt many temptations this is one, the temptation of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> this is the common temptation of the Goſpel, of them that profeſs and believe it, and indeavour to live according to it; wicked men do what they can, that hate godlineſs themſelves, to diſcourage others from it, and diſcover their malice not only in bad Language, but in the baſe uſage of them that fear God. I might ſhew as to malicious reprocahful Language how common a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this hath been for all the Saints in all times, let them be never ſo good they ſhall be ill ſpoken of; and they that are the greateſt bleſſings to the places where they live ſhall be looked upon as the greate ſtroublers of it, as they ſaid <hi>thou art he that troubleſt Iſrael,</hi> whereas wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ahab</hi> and his Idolatries brought their miſery upon them. And ſo <hi>Jeremy</hi> he muſt be ill ſpoken of, he was the man that did all the miſcheif in his days, whereas poor man what did he do, he did only pray for them, and Preach to them, and tell them of thoſe ſins that brought thoſe evils upon them, and yet he muſt be accounted <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man that was the Author of all their miſe<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> no place is fit for him but the Priſon, or the Dungeon; and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, Acts.</hi> 17.5.6. when they came to preach the Goſpel they raiſed up againſt them the worſt, and the baſer ſort of the people, and they muſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154197:32"/> revile them, <hi>theſe are they that turn the World upſide down:</hi> alas what had they turned upſide down: but men's luſts and the Devils King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Devil knew that well enough and therefore he ſo much oppoſed them; alas they are ſo far form being the diſturbers that they are the quieters of a Land; they do not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw but uphold kingdoms, the holy Prophets and the holy People of God are <hi>the Chariots of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and the Horſemen thereof,</hi> and when once they are removed then ruine may be expected; they are the only means that God makes uſe of ſometimes to keep of miſery from a people; let but <hi>Lot</hi> go out of <hi>Sodom</hi> and then Fire, and Brimſtone comes down from Heaven upon them; while <hi>Jeremy</hi> continues praying the Lord forbeares puniſhing; but when God would bring his judgments, then, there comes, <hi>pray not for this people,</hi> This is the common Portion of God's people, they muſt be thought the troublers of the place, they are the men that do all the miſchief, that bring all the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, as if nothing but holineſs was the ruine of the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that is not all, the bad Language they give them, but the bad uſage they meet with is the great temptation, and trouble that the people of God are annoyed by, they do not only open their mouthes againſt them, but they ſtretch forth their hands to vex them; God's people they are the Butt for them to ſhoot the Arrowes of their fury againſt, Lord ſaith
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:154197:33"/> 
               <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 3, 1. <hi>How are they increaſed that trouble me.</hi> Many are they which riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. and it was not their caſe alone but ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>as then he that was borne after the fleſh perſecuted him that was borne after the ſpirit, even ſo it is now:</hi> and ſo it will be to the end of the World, theſe two ſeedes will never agree, wicked men hate the godly at their hearts, and when they have power, and opportunity, they will manifeſt the hatred of their ſpirits by the incivilities they will do them, they will vent their malice, the fury and rage of their hearts in their bud deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24.25. Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the perſons that knew not God, but the Jewes that pretended aquaintance with God, they were <hi>Paul's</hi> great adverſaries. This is the condition of God's people, they ſhall be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with great temptations, with Perſecutions in the world. <hi>David</hi> tells us, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.20. <hi>He was hunted as a Partridge in the Mountains.</hi> Pſal. 102.6.7. <hi>I am like a Pellicane,</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>of the Wilderneſs, I am like an Owle of the Deſart: I watch and am as a Sparrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone upon the Houſe top:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of thoſe brave men, thoſe choiſe Saints, even thoſe, <hi>the World was not worthy of,</hi> Heb. 11.36. <hi>They had trials of cruel, mockings and Scourgings, yea moreover of bonds and impriſonment, they were ſtoned, they were Sawen aſunder, were tempted, were ſlain with the Sword,</hi> &amp;c. The land was not able to bea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e their words and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154197:33"/> their lives; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith this was his caſe, 2 Cor, 11.23. <hi>He was in ſtripes above meaſure, in Priſons more frequent, in deaths oft, of the Jewes five times received I forty ſtripes ſave one, thrice was I beaten with Rods, once was I ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And it was not his caſe alone but of other Saints, not only in his time, but all others muſt in one kind; or other ſuffer and in this ſenſe, <hi>All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer Perſecution:</hi> either the Perſecution of the hand, or the Perſecution of the Tongue, be reproached and vilified, if not abuſed, and impriſoned; if not in reference to their liberties, and eſtates, yet in one kind or other they ſhall be annoyed; Nay the godly many times are moleſted and wronged by thoſe from whom they may in moſt reaſon expect the moſt civility, Pſal. 41.9. <hi>My own familiar friend in whom I truſted which did eat of my bread hath lift up his heel againſt me.</hi> See how many loved Chriſt, and ſee how many of his ſervants, as Chriſt ſaith among the Twelve there was a Judas, Mat. 26.21. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you that one of you ſhall betray me, and they were exceeding ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and began every one of them to ſay to him Lord is it I? and he anſwered and ſaid, he that dippeth his hand with me in the Diſh, the ſame ſhall betray me.</hi> Nay we read the firſt man that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was born in the world that was a good man was a perſecuted man; he was perſecuted to the death, and that by his own brother, Joh. 1
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154197:34"/> 3.12. <hi>Cain was of that wicked one and who ſlew his Brother? and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his own works were evil, and his Brothers good.</hi> One would think he ſhould rather have preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, no, ſuch was the wickedneſs of his ſpirit, that that was the cauſe that he could not be quiet until he was deſtroyed: his own works were evil, and his Brothers good, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle makes the Application in the 13, <hi>verſ. marvel not my brethren if the World hate you:</hi> If you fear God and are willing to ſerve him be, ſure the World will hate you, thoſe that are nearely related to you, you may expect they will be injurious to you.</p>
            <p>Saith Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>think not that I am come to ſend peace on the Earth</hi> (but the fruit of the Goſpel is peace) <hi>but the Sword</hi> (that is trouble will follow that) <hi>I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his Father, and the Daughter againſt her Mother, and the Daughter in Law, againſt her Mother in Law, and a mans foes ſhall be they of his own houſe,</hi> The Preaching of the Goſpel is not the cauſe, but only occaſion through ſome mens imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of it, whom God gives grace to, and others rejecting and oppoſing of it, it doth occaſion diviſions amongſt thoſe that are naturally moſt united; there is a caution given; Jer. 9.4. <hi>take ye heed every one of his neighbour and truſt ye not in any brother; for every brother will utterly ſupplant, and every neighbor will walk with ſlanders,</hi> i. e. raiſe falſe reports of you, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154197:34"/> bring you to ſuffer unjuſtly; though every brother and every neighbour will not; yet many neighbours and many relations will do ſo. That's one great temptation that the people of God have in reference to wicked mens perſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In regard of Sathans temptations they have many troubles too. For thoſe whom Sathan knows he cannot deſtroy for ever, he will do what he can to diſturb here, and though he cannot deſtroy them, yet he will afright them here. Temptations of troubles are the portion of God's people in this world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> The meditation or thought of this truth may be uſeful both to thoſe that are in a proſperous, and them that are in a ſuffering Condition.</p>
            <p>If God's people be under many troubles, many temptations in this world, then you that fear God and yet proſper, let the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſtir you up to a two-fold duty.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To expect troubles, to expect temptations how ever you flouriſh in your out ward man yet do not think proſperity will always laſt. While God bleſſes his people with comfort, and mercy, bleſs him; and praiſe him, but look for an alteration, expect a change. They that at preſent enjoy their eaſe, and ſafety and liberty, and have many comforts, and delights
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154197:35"/> in the world, O uſe the world but do not abuſe it in thoſe bleſſings God gives you, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce as though you rejoyced not, remembr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it will not be always thus with you. Think upon this truth, temptations and trials will befall you, ſooner or later, troubles will be all our portion, remember the daies of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are a coming, the time of ſuffering will come before we go out of this world. Saith Chriſt <hi>in the World you ſhall have trouble</hi> but in me you ſhall have peace.</p>
            <p>Though hitherto many of God's people may have met with no conſiderable temptations, yet they may have their ſhare of them, they may have many of them; let not thoſe that are in a proſperous Condition, in any reſpect let them not always expect Halcyon days, the clouds may ſoon gather, a ſtorm may come before we are aware, and trouble is many times neareſt, when we think it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt off.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As we ſhould expect temptation, and expect trouble; ſo let us prepare for trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Get your ſelves furniſhed with thoſe graces that may ſure your conditions, that you may not be overcome by temptation; O pray, get a ſtock of holineſs that may ſtand you in ſtead in the evil day, and in the hour of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; O be not without faith and meekneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that we ſhall have ſo much need of in the time of trouble. The Scripture tells that we are pilgrims and ſtrangers here on earth, as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154197:35"/> all the godly were in all times, we have a long journey to take from Earth to Heaven, we muſt paſs through the Sea of this World, and the Winds will blow, O let us be prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſtorm for we muſt meet with fowl weather, <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.22.23. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, behold I go bound in the ſpirit unto Jeruſalem not knowing the things that ſhall befall me there,</hi> (only one thing he knew) <hi>Save that the Holy Ghoſt witneſſeth in every City, ſaying that bonds and afflictions abide me.</hi> What ſucceſs I ſhall have in Preaching I cannot tell, or what other things may happen, but I am ſure to meet with troubles here; and why ſhould we expect otherwiſe then this good man did; Now we had need be prepared againſt them, for in every place we are like to find them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let them that ſuffer in the world take heed of raſh judging themſelves; let no Perſon think that his caſe is bad becauſe his condition is ſad, let no Perſon think he his none of God's people becauſe he meets with ſo many troubles, you, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>are in heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs through manyfold temptations.</hi> Let us not think that God doth not love us becauſe he doth afflict us, <hi>Paul</hi> was a pretious ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, one that knew Jeſus Chriſt, and loved him, and yet afflictions and troubles e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where were his portion, Heb. 12.7. <hi>If you endure Chaſtiſements God deals with you as ſons for what ſon is he whom the Father Chaſtens not?</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:154197:36"/> It is not a ſign of the hatred but of the love of God; whom the Lord loves he Chaſtens, and whatever troubles we may meet withal in this world, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. remember this, <hi>the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are accompliſhed in our brethren in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, You are <hi>in heavineſs</hi> through many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Temptations, not only have them, but you are ſenſible of them: from whence the Doctrin is.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, <hi>That the Saints may be in heavineſs through their manyfold temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are in heavineſs, or you are ſadned, you are grieved. God's people may have their ſpirits much ſadned through the variety of troubles they meet with in the world. The word in the Text <hi>you are in Heavineſs,</hi> or you are ſadned comes from a word that ſignifies ſuch grief as brings tears into the eyes; ſuch a grief as is expreſſed by weeping; you are thoſe that even cry, your grief is ſuch that cauſes tears; I the thought of the great troubles you meet with hath ſuch ſorrow and grief, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the troubles of the ſoul but the troubles that God's people meet with in the world they much ſadden their ſpirits and much grive their hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6, 6, 7. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of his Temptations, ſaith he, <hi>I am weary with my groaning, all the Night make I my Bed to ſwim, I water my Couch with my tears;</hi> day and night he was full of griefe, full of weeping <hi>Myne eye is conſumed beeauſe of grief, it waxeth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154197:36"/> old becauſe of all my enemies,</hi> not only the troubles that he had as to his Soul, the thought of his ſins, but the troubles of the world did much affect him, Pſal, 38.6. <hi>I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long.</hi> 8. verſ. <hi>I am feeble and ſore broken, I have roar'd by reaſon of the diſquietneſs of my heart.</hi> And ſo the Church, <hi>Lam</hi> 1.16. the Church having ſpoken of her miſery what, a ſad caſe ſhe was in, in the world, ſaith ſhe, <hi>For theſe things I weep, myne eye runneth down with water, becauſe the comforter that ſhould relieve my Soul is far from me;</hi> and how great the trouble was, that was then the Churches portion, the whole book of <hi>Lamentations</hi> verifies.</p>
            <p>Grace doth not make people inſenſible, they whoſe hearts are ſanctified may lay to heart their troubles. Though grace doth correct, and abate mens paſſions, and rectify nature, yet it doth not deſtroy nature, or natural affections. The Saints here, that were the called and choſen people of God, they had their ſorrow, and grief as well as their gladneſs, the work of grace wherever it is in truth wrought in any ſoul, doth much reſtrain mens violent paſſions; yet when men begin to be good they do not ceaſe to be men. Religion doth not rob people of their ſenſes. The godly have their fears as well as their hopes, &amp; as they have their joys ſo they are not without their ſorrows, you are in heavineſs through manifold temptations. Afflictions are afflictions to them that fear God as well as to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154197:37"/> others, Heb. 12.11. <hi>no chaſhiment for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous but grievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no Perſon think becauſe the croſſes and troubles he meets withal in the World do ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and afflict him, therefore he hath no grace; that ſurely if they had grace they ſhould have no ſuch thing as grief, and trouble of heart. See the Holyeſt men we read of tell us the troubles of their hearts were often inlarged. Though the power of godlineſs doth moderate our affections to things here below, yet it doth not make us inſenſible of what we ſuffer here below. Grace doth not rob men of <hi>Humanity,</hi> as not upon a Civil account, ſo neither doth it upon a Natural account: people do not ceaſe to be men and women when they come to be truly godly; if Perſons were not affected &amp; afflicted with their troubles, afflictions were no afflictons to them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do not therefore paſs ſentence upon thy ſelf as one that is an unconverted Perſon becauſe the great troubles thou meeteſt withal in the world are laid to heart by thee; though grace do diminiſh, yet it doth not deſtroy mens paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>James</hi> 5.17. the Apoſtles us, <hi>Elias was a man ſubject to like paſſions as we are,</hi> though he was a man of exceeding great faith, yet you find him ſometimes a man of great fear. The Scripture records, as his grace, ſo his natural temper, that eminency of grace that was in him, did not deſtroy that that was natural in him. Chriſtianity doth not introduce a Stoical Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, that they do not at all regard how things
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:154197:37"/> go with them; we may have grace in our hearts, and yet lay to heart our ſufferings; we may be truly brought home to God, and yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected through ſenſe of our afflictions in the World.</p>
            <p>Only here let me put in a few cautions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Though God's people are in heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſadneſs through the great troubles that they meet withal in the world; yet, you that fear God, take heed you be not in ſuch heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as thoſe who have no hope, do not ſorrow as them that have no hope, or no ground of hope, for the bleſſing of God upon them here, much leſs for happineſs with God hereafter: rejoyce in the Lord, while you have ſorrow in the world, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>rejoyce in the Lord always,</hi> and he makes a repetition, <hi>and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I ſay rejoyce.</hi> This is his councel to the ſuffering Saints; even when moſt afflicted, as <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. when he was in that great trouble, when his Wives were taken Captive, and his Children, and the people ſpeak of ſtoning <hi>David,</hi> what did he do? but <hi>David</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged himſelf in the Lord his God: ſo ſhould we do when we are diſcouraged as to the world, then we ſhould incourage our ſelves in the Lord our God, <hi>at what time I am afraid, I will truſt in thee;</hi> let not our afflictions here, make us think it will never be otherwiſe hereafter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let not your heavineſs, or trouble, or ſadneſs in the World be joyned with diſcontent; do not murmur becauſe we
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154197:38"/> meet with troubles, let us not think becauſe we are afflicted that others are in a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then our ſelves, becauſe they thrive and and flouriſh in the world, O let us not quarrel at any of God's providences, let us ſay as that good Old man <hi>Eli, It is the Lord, let him do what ſeems him good:</hi> the Lord is good and doth good, and he doth nothing but what is good for us: we have no cauſe to quarrel when God doth afflict us; let us then take care that we do not fret our ſelves to do evil, <hi>for there is no evil in the City but God doth it,</hi> and good is that God that ſends that evil, and all evil ſhall be for good to them that fear God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let your heavineſs be greater for your tranſgreſſions then for any affliction or temptation; let us more grieve for ſin, that is the cauſe of trouble, then for all thoſe troubles that are cauſed by ſin, let us more lay to heart our own corruptions, then all the malice of wicked men, and the afflictions we meet with in the world; we had not known what ſorrow meant had not ſin been in our hearts and been in our lives: let us mourn more for ſin, or however be ſure that our natural ſorrow be accompanyed with ſpiritual ſorrow, that we have that <hi>godly ſorrow that workes repentance unto Salvation:</hi> for worldly ſorrow alone only cauſeth death, O let ſin be more laid to heart and the croſſes in the World leſs laid to heart; let us mourn more, for our tranſgreſſions and we ſhall leſs mind our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:154197:38"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Let not our heavineſs, or ſadneſs, or grief of ſpirit, that is occaſioned through troubles in the World, cauſe us to neglect our duty: let us take care that we do not ſo grieve for what we ſuffer, as to forget what we have to do, let us not ſo mind our miſery as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our duty, or omit our duty to God or Man, in the places of our general and particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which God hath ſet us in the world. When ſorrow is ſo exceſſive that it drives us from God and from his wayes, from delighting in him, we have cauſe then to be in heavineſs for it; we are not ſo to mind what we ſuffer, as to forget what we do. That ſorrow is never like to do us good, nay that ſorrow doth not make us at all to be good that keeps us from doing good; if we once come to that paſs to neglect our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that heavineſs is to be lamented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applicat.</hi> Beloved, we have heard <hi>Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are in heavineſs through manifold temptations,</hi> but let me tell you, If Gods people be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs here, what heavineſs ſhall Gods enemies be in hereafter? If God chaſtiſe his faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſure he will puniſh his enemies; if this be done in a green Tree, what ſhall be done in a dry; if Gods people have their temptations, ſurely wicked men ſhall have their tribulation, <hi>tribulation and anguiſh upon every one that doth evil;</hi> doubtleſs if manifold temptations be the lot of the righteous here, dreadful tribulation will be the portion of the wicked hereafter; doubtleſs the time is coming, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.8. <hi>verſ.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:154197:39"/> The righteous is delivered out of trouble and the wicked cometh in his room:</hi> the time is coming when ſin and ſorrow ſhall be gone from the people of God, and then everlaſting ſorrow ſhall be the portion of all ungodly men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.41. <hi>ver. The Son of Man ſhall ſend forth his Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, and them which do iniquity;</hi> them which follow ſin, deviſe ſin, commit ſin, tempt others to ſin; <hi>he ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fire, there ſhall be wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> there is heavineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: <hi>Then ſhall the righteous ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> If they that fear God be ſo heavy in this World, if the yoak of Chriſt be ſo uneaſie, how intolerable will the miſery of wicked men be in another World? If thoſe that fear God have had ſuch troubles of Spirit, as <hi>David, That they have roared by reaſon of diſquietneſs of heart,</hi> then certainly hypocrites, and unbelievers, and the enemies of God and godlineſs, the time is coming, they ſhall have ſuch a life that they would be glad it might be at an end, but alas it ſhall never end, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.6. <hi>ver. They ſhall ſeek death and ſhall not find it,</hi> and ſhall deſire to dye and death ſhall flee from them. O be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, if the Godly, the pretious Servants, the faithful People of the Moſt High, drink of the bitter cup of Gods wrath; if they taſte the cup of Gods anger, ſure the wicked ſhall drink the dregs of it; if God afflict thoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:154197:39"/> whom he loves, how will he puniſh thoſe whom he hates? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the wicked he ſhall rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, this ſhall be the portion of their cup.</hi> If Gods people be in heavineſs here, if they have manifold temptations, many ſorrows ſhall be to the wicked hereafter.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <p>I Now come to the third Obſervation which is this, <hi>That the temptations that Gods people are exerciſed with ſhall be but for a ſeaſon;</hi> and now for a ſeaſon, ſaith the Apoſtle; if need be, the troubles of Gods people ſhall not laſt always, but for a ſeaſon, or for a little while; yet a little while, it will not be long, it will not always be at this paſs, it will not always be thus ſad with you, <hi>Light is ſown,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and joy for the upright in heart:</hi> Though they may have an hour of darkneſs, and though they that are moſt ſincere, may have an hour of ſorrow, yet light is ſown for them; and as it is ſown for them, ſo it ſhall come up, they ſhall have it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.6, 7. <hi>They that ſow in tears ſhall reap in joy; He that goeth forth and weepeth bearing pretious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come again with rejoycing bringing forth his ſheaves with him.</hi> Gods
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154197:40"/> people ſhall not be always under haches, their troubles are but for a ſeaſon for a while; they are but for a ſeaſon; either for a ſeaſon in this life, or at moſt but for the ſeaſon of this life.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are manytimes but for a ſeaſon in this life; Gods people manytimes out-live their troubles; many temptations that God brings his ſervants into, he brings them out again even in this World; their fits of ſorrow do not laſt always, though they have their ſad paroxiſmes, they have ſome intermiſſion notwithſtanding ſad fits, and yet they have a deliverance: you have heard of the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Job,</hi> and you have heard of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of <hi>Job, Pſal.</hi> 34.19. <hi>ver. Many are the troubles of the righteous,</hi> and what ſhall they always laſt, no, <hi>the Lord delivers them out of them all;</hi> and as it was then, ſo it is verified at this time, (eſpecially thoſe that are the great troubles of the people of God, God doth <hi>with the temptation make away for eſcape:</hi> The Lord took away all <hi>Job</hi> had, but yet he gave him all again; nay the Lord, <hi>Job</hi> 42. gave him twice as much as he had before: God delivered him out of all his adverſity. And as it is ſo ſometimes as to Perſons, ſo it is as to Nations; God manytimes ſaves his people in this World out of the greateſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, he brings them with joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort out of them: we Read often of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Lord ſold them into the hand of their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:154197:40"/> enemies, for ſuch and ſuch ſins as they were guilty of, and yet the Lord raiſed Saviours to them, and delivered them out of the hand of thoſe that hated them. God often in wrath remembers mercy towards his people in this World, <hi>The rod of the wicked,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>ſhall not reſt upon the back of the righteous;</hi> though it may come there, yet it ſhall not ſtay there: God manytimes doth provide a way to eſcape out of the greateſt of his peoples miſeries, and ſometimes he gives them that faith whereby they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that deliverance ſhall come, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.20 21. <hi>verſ. Thou who haſt ſhewed me great and ſoar troubles, ſhalt quicken me again, and ſhalt bring me up from the depthes of the Earth, thou ſhalt increaſe my greatneſs, and comfort me on every ſide.</hi> He was not ſo deep in the pit of affliction, but God would raiſe him up again; and he was not ſo ſurrounded with croſſes, but God would comfort him on every ſide: Yea confident he was of this, and that faith manytimes of deliverance, keeps up their Spirits under the ſenſe of their preſent troubles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.13. <hi>ver.</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, ſpeaking of the good iſſue he hoped for, <hi>I had fainted unleſs I had believed to ſee the goodneſs of the Lord in the Land <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the living:</hi> the thought of his future ſalvation did refreſh and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his Spirit, under the ſenſe of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tribulation.</p>
            <p>Nay, Sometimes though Gods people have
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154197:41"/> not that faith to believe they ſhall be delivered, yet he will ſhew them that mercy to cauſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance; as God is able, ſo he always doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly beyond what his people ask and think, if not beyond what they pray for, yet beyond what they hope, they ſhall have, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.22. <hi>v. I ſaid,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, in my haſte I am cut off from before thine eyes,</hi> but it was far otherwiſe, <hi>never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs thou heardeſt the voice of my ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons when I cried to thee:</hi> I was brought to this paſs, there was no hope of deliverance for me, I did not expect to ſee good day in this World; but God did otherwiſe, he dealt graciouſly with me; I went on in my duty, and God heard me; and as the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.11. <hi>verſ. I ſaid in my haſte all men are lyars:</hi> whoever profeſſed or ſpoke, that any mercy would be ſhewed him, that ever ſalvation ſhould be wrought for him, and that he ſhould be delivered out of the hand of his Perſecutors, he did believe it was a meer ſtory, a very lye, and yet the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred him in his low eſtate; <hi>I was brought low and he helped me, return unto thy reſt O my ſoul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee:</hi> God did ſhew him mercy, though he did not expect mercy; nay, ſuch a mercy as to be delivered in this World: <hi>I ſhall one day fall by the hand of Saul,</hi> and yet <hi>Saul</hi> died, and he lived: Gods people, I ſay, many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are delivered in this World out of eminent dangers, though great, though
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:154197:41"/> long troubles, though ſoar, and though laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet they are not everlaſting, they do not continue as long as their days continue. Many have been under great temptations, ſoar perſecution, and yet have outlived their perſecutors, <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> did even when they were paſt hopes; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>verſ. We were preſſed out of meaſure above ſtrength, inſomuch that we deſpaired even of life, but we had the ſentence of death in our ſelves, that we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the dead: Who delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver; in whom we truſt that he will yet deliver us:</hi> and he tells <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10, 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> of the great troubles and perſecutions that came to him, <hi>but out of them all the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him:</hi> and ſo in the ſame Epiſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16, 17. <hi>ver.</hi> when he was brought before <hi>Nero, all men forſook me, yet God did not forſake me, the Lord ſtood with me, and ſtrengthened me, and I was delivered out of the mouth of the Lyon:</hi> though he was very near unto death, yet his life was preſerved, God did make, with that ſoar temptation, a way to eſcape. The troubles of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall be but for a ſeaſon, ſometimes they are but for a ſeaſon in this life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, At the moſt they ſhall be but for the ſeaſon of this life, they ſhall laſt no longer; ſo one Paraphraſes upon the words, they are but for a ſeaſon, as long as this ſhort
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154197:42"/> life laſts, ſo long you may be afflicted, if there be occaſion for it, but then there is an end of all: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>verſ. Our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction which is but for a ſeaſon,</hi> but for a moment, it ſhall not be hereafter, it ſhall be but here while the moment of this life laſts, then it vaniſhes away; when our lives go, if we fear God, all our troubles will go away with them: there is a time for every thing, this preſent time is the time of the Saints afflictions, the time that Gods people ſuffer, this is the time of temptation of all that fear God; when this life is at an end, afflictions will be out of ſeaſon, there will be none of them when this life ends, the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of the godly will then be at an end; death puts a period to all their troubles, they continue but while they have their abode in this earthly tabernacle, no longer ſhall any croſs or affliction be their portion, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.13. <hi>verſ. Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi> Bleſſed are they though they ſeem the moſt curſed of any people, in ſome reſpects, while they live; yet bleſſed are they when they dye, for they reſt from their labours, that is though not from their labour of ſervice, and love to God and his people; yet from their labour of ſorrow, they ſhall then have no burden of perſecution or affliction to bear; as no evil ſhall be done by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:154197:42"/> them, ſo no evil then ſhall be ſuffered by them; as they ſhall not know what ſin means in another World, ſo neither ſhall they underſtand what ſorrow means; weeping and wailing, all tears then ſhall be wiped from their faces, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting joy ſhall be upon their heads; no diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of Spirit ſhall be the Saints lot in another World; no evil work, nor work of iniquity ſhall ever follow them; mens Peſecutors may follow them to the grave, but then they muſt leave them, then your bodies ſhall go into your graves in peace, and your ſouls ſhall go to God that gave them, to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, that are without ſin, and without ſuffering, that are for ever ſerving God, and continually injoying God. In Gods preſence where Gods people ſhall be after this World, there is no part of their lives that is imbittered to them; there is fulneſs of joy, and their is pleaſure for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more at Gods right hand; it is not only ſome little comfort is given them, a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> this World to bear up their Spirits, but there the joy ſhall be everlaſting pleaſure for evermore. O well may believers ſay, as God by the Prophet, <hi>Say you to the righteous it ſhall be well with him;</hi> though it be very ill with him whiles he lives, yet it ſhall be well with him when he dyes, his troubles he ſhall ſee they were but for a ſeaſon, though he may have many inconveniences in his earthly taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, yet he ſhall find nothing of diſlike
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154197:43"/> when he comes to Gods everlaſting habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Why is it ſo? Why ſhall the temptations of the Godly be but for a ſeaſon? Why ſhall their affliction not laſt allways? I will give you a two fold account of it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Becauſe of the mercifulneſs of God, he is a God of tender mercy, he compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onates all his creatures, in all reſpects, but much more them who are not only the work of his hands, but the delight of his heart, as all that fear and love him are, he hath great kindneſs for them; and this account is given, why the Lord will not always chide his people? he is a merciful God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8, 9. <hi>verſ. The Lord is merciful and gracious, ſlow to anger, and plenteous in mercy,</hi> and then it follows, <hi>he will not always chide, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will he keep his anger for ever;</hi> angry he may be with his children, when they are faulty and diſobedient, <hi>But he will not keep his anger forever;</hi> Why? the verſes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing declare, <hi>Like as a Father pitieth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo the Lord pitieth them that fear him; for he knows our frame, he remembers we are but duſt:</hi> God knows what frail creatures his people are, and though ſome chiding they may bear, yet his frowns they are not able to undergo; that is the reaſon God gives, why he would not ſhew himſelf always diſpleaſed with his people, he ſhould break their hearts with ſuch thoughts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.16, 17. <hi>verſ. I
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154197:43"/> will not contend for ever, neither will I be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways wroth,</hi> why? <hi>for the Spirit ſhould fail before me, and the Soul which I have made:</hi> the very heart of Gods people would be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a long continuance of their troubles, and therefore he will in wrath remember mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as it follows, <hi>For the iniquity of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetuouſneſs was I wroth, and ſmote him; I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on frowardly in the way of his heart: I have ſeen his ways and will heal him; I will lead him alſo, and reſtore comforts unto him, and to his mourners.</hi> I know that he is not able always to bear my afflicting hand, I will take it of, it ſhall be but a little while; the rod is upon his back but it ſhall not reſt there, I will manifeſt my love again to him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7, 8. <hi>verſ. For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee: In a little wrath I hid my ſelf from thee, for a moment; but with everlaſting kindneſs will I have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer.</hi> A little wrath, but a great deal of Love; a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, a moment, God hides himſelf, but eternally will he manifeſt himſelf, and his love to his people. Beloved, the mercy and compaſſion of God is ſuch, that he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide a way for his peoples deliverance out of their troubles. As God will not himſelf more immediately afflict his people always, ſo neither will he ſuffer others to afflict his people; but he will be ſure not to ſuffer <hi>The
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154197:44"/> rod of the wicked to reſt upon the back of the righteous,</hi> Why? <hi>Leaſt the righteous put forth his hand to iniquity,</hi> leaſt their temptations be too ſtrong for them, and ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>God is faithful, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above what you are able, but will with the temptation make a way to eſcape that you may be able to bear it:</hi> You ſhall have ſuch troubles as may ſometimes afflict and humble you, but you ſhall not have ſuch troubles as ſhall quite deject, and cauſe your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to fail before him, that is the firſt Reaſon, becauſe of the mercifulneſs of God.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Becauſe of the faithfulneſs of God; God hath ſaid he will deliver his people, and he will be as good as his word; though men break, God will keep his Covenant; he is a God of truth, he hath methods to deliver his people out of temptation, he will make a way to eſcape. Now God hath made (I cannot ſtand to ſhew) God hath made many pretious promiſes for the redeeming of his people out of their adverſity; he will ſhew kindneſs to them, though he may be angry, yet he will not always chide: and though he may afflict them, yet he will not forſake them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid in regard of his Father <hi>David, What thou haſt ſpoken with thy mouth thou haſt fulfilled it with thine hand, as it is this day:</hi> and ſo it is true of all perſons that fear God, what God
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:154197:44"/> ſpeaks he will fulfil, <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but not one jot or title of Gods Word ſhall paſs away unfulfilled;</hi> as Gods threatning of Judgment againſt the wicked ſhall be made good, ſo certainly ſhall the promiſes of mercy made to the righteous; <hi>All the promiſes of God are yea and amen, in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applicat.</hi> Now then to apply this, in a word, If this be ſo as we hear, the temptations of the godly, the afflictions and troubles they meet with, will be but for a ſeaſon; Let this quiet our hearts under ſufferings, <hi>viz.</hi> the conſideration of this, That they will be but for a ſeaſon, they will be but for a ſhort time, they will not be always; are we afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, remember the time is coming we ſhall be comforted, hath God laid any trouble upon us, as to our inward or outward man, upon our perſons or relations, in private or other reſpects, it will not be always ſo; theſe troubles they ſhall be but for a ſeaſon, and this ſeaſon will not laſt always: let us not be troubled, or though we be troubled, let this keep us from being overtroubled; let this quiet our ſpirits under trouble, the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this truth, That they will be but for a ſhort time, for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Two things may quiet our Spirits under the greateſt of miſeries and croſſes in this
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154197:45"/> World; if we conſider either how juſt they are, or how ſhort they be.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we conſider the equity of them, all the troubles we meet with in the World, they are very juſt upon us; God doth not afflict us but there is a cauſe for it; there is need of it and cauſe for it; God is never diſpleaſed, but we have provoked him; he never hides his face, but we have given him cauſe for it; nay, God is never ſo angry with his people as he might be; we may all ſay with the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.10. <hi>ver. He hath not dealt with us after our ſins, nor rewarded us according to our iniquities:</hi> What ever ſad condition we are in, beſure it is not ſo ſad as we deſerve; is God angry with us? why he might manifeſt his hot diſpleaſure againſt us; is he very angry? why truly he might be more angry then ever he ſhews himſelf in this World to any of his people: God might to the beſt of men render his anger with fury, and his rebukes with flames of fire. <hi>Ezra</hi> ſpeaking of the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Jews, which were very great, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.13. <hi>ver.</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Thou O God haſt puniſhed us leſs then our iniquities deſerve:</hi> How did God cut of thouſands of them? how many periſhed by the Sword, Plague, and other Judgments? and thoſe that were left alive, were carried into captivity: we were puniſhed, I but not ſo as we deſerve; our troubles were great, but they might have
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154197:45"/> been greater; <hi>Thou haſt puniſhed us leſs then our iniquities deſerve;</hi> our treſpaſs is grown up unto the Heavens, and we might all of us have been thrown into Hell: God ſuffers us to live, and hath not puniſhed us as our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities deſerve; ſo that we are on this ſide the Grave, nay that we are on this ſide Hell, it is a mercy; alas are our troubles great? our ſins are greater; are our temptations, our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, many? our ſins are more; there is no body that hath ſo many troubles, but he may ſit down and ſoon count the number of his croſſes, but who can count the number of any mans ſins; our croſſes, our troubles, are ſoon numbred, but our impieties, nay our iniquities are innumerable, they are more then the hairs of our head, and cannot be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; have we many croſſes? remember we might have had more croſſes; remember our ſorrows are not ſo many as our ſins; we may well therefore ask the queſtion when any perſons heart is diſquieted, ſo as to be diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, and fret at providence that is ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting, as the Church, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39. <hi>verſ. Wherefore doth a living man complain, a man for the puniſhment of his ſins?</hi> Thou art puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what then? what cauſe to complain? it is for thy ſin, thy ſin deſerves this puniſhment, and <hi>What a living man complain?</hi> thou mighteſt have been in the grave; thou art here yet on Earth, thou mighteſt have been long ago in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154197:46"/> Hell; and <hi>What a living man, and complain for the puniſhment of his ſin?</hi> and as they ſay, we may all ſay under any of our troubles, <hi>It is of the Lords mercy that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions fail not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As our troubles are very Juſt, ſo they ſhall not be very long, they ſhall be but for a little while; as the pleaſure of ſinners, ſo the perplexity of Saints ſhall be but for a ſeaſon, but for a ſeaſon; <hi>Our light afflictions which are but for a moment,</hi> if any of our troubles ſhould laſt as long as our lives laſt, that will not be long; for as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>What is your life, it is even as a vapour that ſoon paſſeth away:</hi> if always afflicted whileſt thou liveſt, remember the time is haſtning that thou ſhalt dye, and then no longer diſturbed: this ſaddens thy Spirit, that ſo long thy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath been uncomfortable; let this ſupport thee, thou ſhalt not be for ever miſerable, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13. <hi>ver. Though ye have lien among the pots, yet ſhall ye be as the wings of a Dove, covered with Silver, and her feathers with yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Gold:</hi> though you have been in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and uncomfortable eſtate, yet the time of joy and proſperity is coming to you; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that temptations may be ſore, and great, and may ſeem to be long, yet they will be but for a time, they will not laſt always, theſe clouds will be blown over; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rain will come Sun-ſhine; though the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:154197:46"/> Lord hide his face for a moment; weeping may endure for a night, but joy comes in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: I may ſay to many of us, let our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles be what they will, thoſe that believe in God, and endeavour faithfully to ſerve him, to them is alotted the more troubles: If we have lived but any conſiderable time in the World, I may ſay to you that are elder, as the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, <hi>The night is far ſpent,</hi> the night of your ſorrow is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at an end, the day of the reſurrection a coming, that day of gladneſs when you ſhall not know what affliction means; when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> asked <hi>Jacob</hi> how old he was, he tells him, and afterwards ſaith he, <hi>Few and evil have been the days of my life.</hi> If the days of our life be evil, let this comfort us they are but few, they ſhall be few; you know the life of man it is not many years, many of us have out-lived moſt of thoſe years; it will be <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the time is coming all theſe ſorrows and miſeries will be out of ſeaſon. The length of a trouble doth greaten it, though it be ſmall in it ſelf; a little burden carryed a great way is great, and ſo the ſhortneſs of a trouble doth much leſſen it; though our troubles be great, yet remember they ſhall not laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, they ſhall be but for a ſeaſon; <hi>Lift up therefore the hands that hang down, and the feeble knees,</hi> I may ſay as the Apoſtle doth.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:154197:47"/>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>If need be,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>you are in heavineſs through manifold temptations; If need be,</hi> why then this is implied, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there is need you ſhould have temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there is a neceſſity for it: from whence the Doctrine is this,</p>
            <p>Doct. I. <hi>That there is need ſometimes why the people of God, the faithful people of God ſhould be under manifold temptations, ſhould be afflicted in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As diſtempered bodies need Phyſick as well as food; ſo Souls that are diſtempered with ſin, need afflicting providences as well as holy Ordinances: Gods own children are not ſuch, but ſometimes they need the rod as well as the Word; they need affliction as well as Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; there is need, if need be; there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a neceſſity in the ordinary way of Gods providence, why Gods people ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der trouble.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>If any ſhould ask what need there is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thought to have Anſwered it in theſe twelve Particulars, but I will only ſpeak to ſome few of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is need why Gods people ſhould be afflicted or tempted, to diſcover the truth of their graces; there is need there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of affliction, that they may be made to appear what indeed they are; times of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154197:47"/> trouble are times of tryal; and thence it is that afflictions are in this verſe called by the name of temptations, <hi>Through manifold temptations,</hi> that is, through manifold troubles and trials, or through diverſe trials, diverſe troubles: I ſay afflictions are here, and ſo often elſewhere, called temptations, becauſe they try what people are, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.10. <hi>ver. Thou O God haſt proved us, thou haſt tried us, as Silver is tried:</hi> How were they tried? how? by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the troubles they met with in the World; as the 11. <hi>ver.</hi> ſhews, <hi>Thou brought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt us into the net, thou layeſt affliction upon our loyns:</hi> thou haſt tried us, that is by theſe afflictions thou haſt tried us; as mettals are tried by the fire, ſo are Gods people, in the furnace of affliction, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. <hi>ver. That the trial of your faith, being much more pretious then of Gold that periſhes, though it be tried with fire, might be found unto praiſe and honour, and glory, at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Theſe temptations are for your trial, <hi>Job</hi> 23.20. <hi>ver. Job</hi> ſpeaking to God ſaith, <hi>He knows the way that I take, and when he hath tried me, I ſhall come forth as Gold: When he hath tried me,</hi> how is that? why, that is by the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als he ſends me, he diſcovers what I am; then I ſhall come forth as Gold; by troubles and croſſes in the World, he tries his people, he tries their faith in him, and their love to him, he diſcovers their ſincerity.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:154197:48"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But what need of theſe trials?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may Anſwer, Negatively, and Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Negatively, God need not try us by troubles, for he knows what we are; he knows what we are before he afflicts us, and what we ſhall be when we are afflicted; thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeſt my thoughts a far of; God is fully acquainted with all our ways, not only the ways that we have gone in, but the ways that we will go; God can tell when we proſper, what we ſhall do when we come to ſuffer, he underſtands our thoughts a far of; God can tell when we are in flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition, whether we ſhall flinch from his Service when it is like to bring us to ſuffering; <hi>The heart is deceitful above all things, and yet I the Lord ſearch the heart, and try the reins:</hi> Though man doth not know his own heart, how he ſhall carry himſelf in a time of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet God knows it; 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.12, 13. <hi>ver.</hi> God could tell when <hi>Haziel</hi> was a Subject, what he ſhould do when he was a King; he could tell what a bloody cruel man he ſhould be; God could tell who ſhould be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Perſecutors long before they knew it; they are not needful in reference to God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.23, 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, it is ſaid there of him, <hi>Many believed in his Name, when they ſaw the miracles that he did: But Jeſus did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf unto them, becauſe he knew all men,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:154197:48"/> and needed not that any ſhould teſtifie of man, for he knew what was in man:</hi> it is ſpoken of him as he was God, God doth not need to ſend troubles to diſcover to him what we are, God knows us before hand.</p>
            <p n="2">II. But Affirmatively, God ſeeth it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to diſcover to our ſelves, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to others what we are; and in theſe two reſpects there is need of temptations, for the trial of Gods people, and ſometimes they are a means to diſcover us to our ſelves, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to others: Sometimes to our ſelves, and they diſcover men ſometimes for the better, ſometimes for the worſe; many perſons that fear God, have worſe thoughts of themſelves then they ought to have, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now God brings them to a fiery tryal, and they ſee through the help of God they are inabled to ſtand out againſt all oppoſition; then they begin to think there is ſomething of good in my Soul, and they manifeſt the truth of grace. And then ſometimes for the worſe; many a man and woman hath better opinions of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves then they have ground for, and the troubles they meet with in the World they plainly diſcover it: God brings them to this paſs, you muſt either diſown the truth, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny your ſelves as to the World; you muſt either lay down that godlineſs you ſeem to have, or lay down your livelyhood, or lay down your lives; and now they ſee, or may
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:154197:49"/> ſee they were not the men they took them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for, they ſee how that the truths of Jeſus Chriſt lay not ſo near their hearts as they thought for; they are willing rather to part with that faith and love they have, then to part with thoſe good things they have; many a perſon it is thus with: Sometimes they diſcover the weakneſs of grace, ſometimes the want of grace; ſometimes the weakneſs of grace, <hi>Peter</hi> thought when the Lord told him of ſuffering, <hi>That all ſhould be offended becauſe of him, that he ſhould never be offended; Though all men forſake thee, yet will not I;</hi> and yet <hi>Peter</hi> when he comes to trial, his Faith ſtaggers; and ſo ſometimes it diſcovers the total want of grace, that people are other manner of perſons then they took themſelves for; times of affliction they manifeſt that many are of another manner of Spirit then they did imagine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Afflictions diſcover not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to themſelves, but they diſcover them to others; diſcover them to the World, make it known what people are; and ſo ſometimes for the better, many are thought worſe of in the World then indeed they do deſerve; the people of God are often judged a company of Hypocrites, there is no ſuch thing as good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, faith, and holineſs, in them; and if they come to ſuffer, you ſhall ſee what they will do; many are their evil ſurmiſes, and the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154197:49"/> Devil if he cannot Perſecute them, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them: now God lets the World ſee that theſe people are miſtaken, his Servants were ſuch as loved him in truth; when it comes to this, that they muſt leave all or not follow Chriſt; they count not their life dear to them, all is nothing then to Chriſt. The ſtedfaſtneſs of Gods people in times of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, teſtifies to the World, that they that were called Hypocrites were the moſt upright per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that lived: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19. <hi>ver. There are diviſions among you, and I partly believe it: For there muſt be alſo Hereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you:</hi> That it may appear that they are indeed lovers of the Truth, they will own it in ſuch a time when it is ſo much oppoſed; that they that are approved of God may be made manifeſt to the World, that the wicked may ſay, though ſome are covetous, yet all are not bad men as they would think. And ſometimes for the worſe to many, becauſe they are not openly profane, are judged by the multitude that they are religious perſons; but when the Profeſſion of Religion becomes dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, they then begin to be troubled, the World then ſees what they are. In hazardous times, good men are made a ſpectacle to the World, and Angels, and Men; the Angels, the good and bad; the Angels of light, and the Feinds of darkneſs; and the World both of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154197:50"/> godly and ungodly, ſee what men they are, who were not before acquainted with them; God makes it manifeſt that many that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed much, never yet loved him, <hi>&amp;c. Many,</hi> ſaith Chriſt in that Parable of the ſeeds, <hi>they received the Word with joy,</hi> but they had no root in themſelves; they endure but for a while, and when Perſecution ariſeth, by and by they are offended: What muſt I ſerve God and ſuffer? Truly if this be the fruit of this ſervice, I ſhall have no mind to it; many their hearts ſay as thoſe wicked ones, <hi>Job</hi> 21.14, 15. <hi>verſ. What is the Almighty that we ſhould ſerve him? and what profit ſhould we have, if we pray unto him?</hi> What ſhall we get by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering? why if this be the way, they will not walk in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Jews would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Proſelites in the days of <hi>David,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then the fear of <hi>David</hi> was upon all round about him; nor would they admit of them in the days of <hi>Solomon,</hi> becauſe then out of love to the peace and proſperity that he had in the World, they might imbrace the truth of Religion, which in their hearts they did not delight in. Many men do make uſe of Religion ſometimes out of fear, and ſometimes out of love; out of fear of ſuffering when Religion is not owned, and out of hopes of getting by Religion when it is in eſteem. The falſeneſs of peoples hearts is ſeen in this, in love to their neighbour; they have a great
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:154197:50"/> love for them that are rich, but none for them that are poor; <hi>The rich hath many friends, but the poor is hated of his neighbour:</hi> This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the falſneſs of peoples hearts in reference to their love to God; their love to the people of God is diſcovered in this, that they will ſpeak well for them, and aſſociate with them, when God is pleaſed to bleſs them in the World; but if God once come to afflict them, they deſire to have no more to do with them: Amongſt many profeſſing Iſraelites there are but few <hi>Nathaniels,</hi> few that are Iſraelites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: and the times of ſuffering manifeſt what people are.</p>
            <p>Again, There is a great deal of need of trouble and trials, to bring Gods people to more earneſt praying to God, that they may more firmly and conſtantly ſeek him: when Gods people are involved in trouble, cannot tell which way to turn themſelves, then they will go to God for help; when <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſaid, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. ſpeaking of his enemies in Prayer to God, <hi>Wilt not thou judge them? for we have no might againſt this great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that cometh up againſt us: neither know we what to do, but our eyes are to thee,</hi> our eyes are upon thee: Truly when people are at this paſs, in referance to Perſonal or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſuffering, when they do not know what to do, then their eyes are upon God, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154197:51"/> then their hearts are to God, then God ſhall hear always of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord knows if proſperity drives us away from him, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction will bring us in to him; the Prodigal that cared not for his Father while his eſtate laſted, when poverty was come, <hi>I will ariſe ſaith he, and go to my Father.</hi> As long as we can have Friends, Comforts, and Mercies to delight in, we do not take ſo much delight and pleaſure in drawing near to God, God will let us have nothing elſe to delight in, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.16. <hi>verſ. Lord, in trouble they have viſited thee:</hi> when thy chaſtning was upon them; they that would not come at God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they would viſit him in trouble, and they powred out Prayer; they that did but ſay a Prayer before, they now ſhall Pray a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Pray it heartily too.</p>
            <p>Croſſes and troubles will make men mind Religious Duties, that before they little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: Upon the worſt of men it hath this influence ſometimes; the Perſian Meſſenger ſaid thus, when the Grecians hotly purſued our Hoſt, and we muſt needs venture over that great River that was now frozen, but was beginning to thaw: <hi>Then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>did I behold many of thoſe Gallants who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed before, and ſo boldly maintained that there was no God, I ſaw every one upon his knees raying that the Ice might hold untill he got
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:154197:51"/> over.</hi> O then nothing but Pr<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>yer will ſerve their turn? <hi>I will go and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eturn to my place,</hi> and I will diſtreſs and diſturb them, <hi>and in their affliction they <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſeek me early.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154197:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
